<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!-- $Id -->
<?oxygen RNGSchema="swinburne.rnc" type="compact"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [
<!ENTITY sb "<hi xmlns='http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0' rendition='#u'>should be</hi>">
<!ENTITY imgpath "/swinburne/images/swinburne/">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="acs0000505-01">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Supplementary Material to the <title>Uncollected Letters of Algernon Charles
                        Swinburne</title>
                </title>
                <author>
                    <persName key="acs">Algernon Charles Swinburne</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="editor">
                   <persName key="meyers">Terry L. Meyers</persName>
                </editor>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="includes/publisher.xml"/>
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="includes/pubPlace.xml"/>
                <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="includes/pubDate.xml"/>
                <availability xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <p> Copyright &#169; 2005-2012 Terry L. Meyers. </p>
                    <p>
                        <!--Creative Commons License-->This work is licensed under an <ref
                            target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/3.0/">Attribution-Noncommercial-Share Alike 3.0 Unported License</ref>. </p>
                </availability>
                <!-- Three docs were combined into once; hence three old IDs.-->
                <idno type="nines"><!-- old ID:intro -->uclintro00</idno>
                <idno type="nines"><!-- old ID:index to appendix b-->uclindxb00</idno>
                <idno type="nines"><!-- old ID:addenda -->ucladdnd00</idno>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic>
                        <editor><persName key="meyers">Terry L. Meyers</persName></editor>
                        <title>Supplementary Material to the <title>Uncollected Letters of Algernon Charles
                            Swinburne</title></title>
                    </analytic>
                    
                    <monogr>
                        <title>The Algernon Charles Swinburne Project</title>
                        <editor><persName key="jawalsh">John A. Walsh</persName></editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                                href="includes/publisher.xml"/>
                            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                                href="includes/pubPlace.xml"/>
                            <date xml:id="sort_date" when="2012"/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="includes/tagsDecl.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="includes/collex_genres.xml" xpointer="element(collex_genres)"/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef target="#collex_genre_letters"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change n="svninfo"> $Id: acs0000499-01.xml 1094 2010-01-12 02:39:26Z jawalsh $ $Rev:
                687 $ $Date: 2010-01-11 21:39:26 -0500 (Mon, 11 Jan 2010) $ $Author: jawalsh $
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <!-- questions for Terry:
          
          * should double hyphens be converted to em dashes?
          * two note references labeled "2" in 321B?
          * Ourang-utan?
          * CBEL3 (title?)
          * Old 874A note replaced with new
    -->
    <text xml:id="acs0000505-01-content" type="correspondence">
        <body>
            <pb n="1" rendition="#suppress" facs="dummy"/>
            <!--<head rendition="#styled">Supplementary Material to the <title>Uncollected Letters of Algernon Charles
                    Swinburne</title>, 3 vols. (London: Pickering and Chatto, 2005). </head>-->
            <div xml:id="intro">
                <index indexName="nav"/>
                <head rendition="#styled">Introduction</head>
              <p>At this site I correct a number of errors in <ref target="https://www.routledge.com/products/9781851967742">my edition</ref> and especially take the opportunity to add new material, including a number of letters from and to Swinburne.  I am grateful to Catherine Trippett of Random House UK for permission to post here Swinburne letters still under copyright.  New too is an article, illustrated with photographs, about Swinburne’s funeral and the controversy associated with it. </p>
                <p>Especially helpful is an <ref type="simple" target="#indexappendixb">index to
                        Appendix B</ref> (in vol. III, pp. 323-368). That appendix contains new
                    material pertaining to 291 of Swinburne's letters published by Cecil Lang,
                        <title> The Swinburne Letters</title>, 6 vols. (New Haven: Yale University
                    Press, 1959-1962): corrections, locations of holographs, identifications,
                    datings, and the like. The index will make those more easily accessible. </p>
                <p> I am grateful to John Walsh, editor of The Swinburne
                    Project, for making these corrections and additions possible. </p>
                <p> And I would be pleased to receive queries or further errata,
                which I will add here from time to time. </p>
                <signed>
                    <ref xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" target="mailto:tlmeye@wm.edu"
                        >Terry L. Meyers</ref>, Chancellor Professor of English
                    <lb/> The College of William and Mary in Virginia </signed>
            </div>
            <div>
                <figure rendition="#center" rend="min-height:603px;">
                    <graphic url="&imgpath;acs0000505-01-000.gif" rend="border:0;"/>
                    <head>A pencil drawing (from a photograph) by Charles Fairfax Murray, inscribed
                        by Swinburne, "Algernon Ch. Swinburne / To my friend F. Gledstanes Waugh /
                        May 26th/68," The drawing, heretofore unpublished, is in the collection of
                        Terry Meyers. Copyright. All rights reserved.<!-- [<ref
                            target="&imgpath;acs0000499-01-000.gif">view
                            larger image</ref>]--></head>
                    <figDesc>A pencil drawing (from a photograph) by Charles Fairfax Murray,
                        inscribed by Swinburne, "Algernon Ch. Swinburne / To my friend F. Gledstanes
                        Waugh / May 26th/68," The drawing, heretofore unpublished, is in the
                        collection of Terry Meyers. Copyright. All rights reserved.</figDesc>
                </figure>
            </div>
            
            <div xml:id="addenda">
                <index indexName="nav"/>
                <head rendition="#styled">Addenda, Corrigenda, and Errata</head>
                <div>
                    <p> The sections below separate what I regard as the more
                        important material from the less important. </p>
                    <p> The publication date of the edition is given as 2005 in
                        vol. 1, and sometimes 2004, sometimes 2005 in vol. II. In vol. III, I have
                        seen only 2004. All should be 2005, although the edition was actually published
                        in November 2004.</p>
                    <signed>
                        <persName>Terry L. Meyers</persName>, Chancellor Professor of English<lb/>
                        <orgName>The College of William and Mary in Virginia</orgName>
                    </signed>
                    <dateline>
                        <date when="2005-11">March 2012</date>
                    </dateline>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="mi1">
                    <index indexName="nav"/>
                    <head rendition="#center #styled">Vol I.—The More Important</head>
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>p. xv, note 1. I should clarify my anecdote about Swinburne Island.  I thought at the time that the entire island (an artificial one) had been removed as an impediment to shipping.  However, I had been misinformed; after being used to quarantine immigrants, the island had been abandoned and its buildings razed, but the island did and does still exist.  It is not named, as I knew of course, after the poet (his father, Admiral Swinburne, does, however, John Mayfield told me, have a geographic feature named after him, in Canada, at the south tip of Prince of Wales Island [71°12'N 99°09'W]).</item>
                        <item>p. xxi. To note 1 should be added:<p> The desire
                                by the Commonwealth of Virginia to deter scholars from studying
                                sexuality and Swinburne has an antecedent in England. In <title
                                    level="a">Forbidden Document</title> (<title>Leader
                                    Magazine</title>, 20 May 1950, p. 10), Woodrow Wyatt, M.P.,
                                takes to task officials at the British Museum who refused permission
                                to Randolph Hughes to read a number of letters and poems by
                                Swinburne as well as Edmund Gosse’s <title level="a">An Essay (with
                                    Two Notes) on Swinburne</title> (<title>Letters</title>, VI,
                                233-48). The matter was discussed in the House of Commons in April,
                                May, and July 1950.</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 18A. p. 11. To note 2 should be added: <p>
                                An unrecorded glimpse of Swinburne at Oxford is afforded in an
                                interview with one of his contemporaries, James Bryce (1838–1922).
                                Bryce affirms that discussions in Old Mortality occurred
                                <quote>over tea
                                and toast</quote>
                                (not all biographers have wanted to believe this) and recalls
                                Swinburne as a student of <quote>brilliant gifts</quote>: <cit
                                    rendition="#block">
                                    <quote rendition="#blockquote #nq">
                                    <p> Swinburne, who was a fascinating companion, with great
                                        social charm, has always seemed to me the most brilliant
                                        members [sic] of this group. In all he wrote, as well as in
                                        his talk, we discerned the genius that has since been so
                                        universally recognized. I remember a striking little poem he
                                        recited at one of our annual festivals, and can still
                                        recollect by heart his admirable parodies of what was then
                                        called the ‘spasmodic school of poets’ [see the poems by
                                        ‘Ernest Wheldrake’ in Swinburne’s purported review in
                                            <title>Undergraduate Papers</title> (February-March
                                        1858), reprinted in <title>New Writings by
                                        Swinburne</title>, pp. 81-7]. He had been educated at Eton,
                                        but it was as much his own fondness for study as anything
                                        his school had done that gave him his wide knowledge of the
                                        Greek poets and mastery of Greek verse. He was also
                                        extraordinarily well read in French as well as in English
                                        literature, a fervent admirer of Victor Hugo, and, like
                                        pretty nearly all of us a no less fervent denouncer of Louis
                                        Napoleon, who was then Emperor in France.</p>
                                    </quote>
                                    </cit>
                                    In a lengthy disquisition on Browning’s reputation at mid-century, Bryce adds that
                            <cit
                                rendition="#blockquote">
                                <quote rendition="#block #nq">
                                    <p rend="margin-bottom:0;padding-bottom:0;"> It was Swinburne who, by reading some of Browning’s poems to
                                        us at one of our meetings, I think in 1858, first introduced
                                        us to the work of that great poet. I recollect, as if it was
                                        yesterday, his reading aloud of 
                                        <title level="a" rendition="#sq">The Statue and the Bust</title>
                                        and <title level="a" rendition="#sq">The Heretic’s Tragedy,</title>
                                        with, I think also, <title level="a" rendition="#sq">Bishop
                                        Blougram’s Apology.</title></p></quote>
                                    <bibl rendition="#ti-3" rend="padding-top:0;margin-top:0;">
                                        (“Our Need is Poets, Says James Bryce,” <title>New York
                                            Times</title>, 29 April 1907, p. 1)</bibl>
                                </cit> Gerald Monsman is skeptical that Swinburne read <title
                                    level="a">Bishop Blougram’s Apology</title> to Old Mortality
                                both because the poem is so long and because it is not recorded in
                                the society’s Minute Book (“Old Mortality at Oxford,” <title>Studies
                                in Philology</title>, 67 [1970], 367n).
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 35A. p. 15. In note 1, Hallem <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            Hallam</item>
                        <item>Letter 35A. p. 15. In note 4, <title>Crew</title>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <title>Crewe</title><lb/> Add a note: See also my <bibl><title level="a">Swinburne’s <title>Will Drew and Phil Crewe &amp; Frank Fane</title>: A Swinburne Enigma,</title> <title>The Book Collector,</title> <biblScope unit="volume">56</biblScope>:<biblScope type="issue">1<date>(Spring 2007)</date></biblScope>, <biblScope unit="page">31-34</biblScope>.</bibl></item>
                      <item>
                        Letter 70A  p. 30.  To note 1 should be added: 
                        <p>For more on Mary Gordon, her life and her work, see Jeremy Mitchell and Janet Powney, "A Forgotten Voice: Moral Guidance in the Novels of Mary Gordon (Mrs. Disney Leith), with a Bibliography," <title>The Victorian</title> [Online], 2.1 (2014): <ptr target="http://journals.sfu.ca/vict/index.php/vict/article/view/82"/>.</p>
                      </item>
                        
                        <item>Letter 121B. p. 64. In the last line of paragraph 3, “is charming”
                                <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> subscripted (and the previous
                            line’s superscript should also be subscript)</item>
                        <item>Letter 122B. p. 66. In note 1, Herfordshire should
                                be Hertfordshire</item>
                        <item>Letter 134A. p. 70. In ll. 14-15, /- <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> closed up</item>
                      <item><!-- jawalsh: added 2015-11-02 -->
                        Letter 148A.  p. 76. To note 6 might be added this: 
                        <p>Several other recent discoveries bear on Swinburne’s literary career and fame.</p>
                        <p>Richard Crawly’s satirical survey in 1868 of contemporary authors deals with <title rendition="#i">Atalanta in Calydon</title> and <title rendition="#i">Poems and Ballads</title> (See <title rendition="#i">Horse and Foot, or Pilgrims to Parnassus</title> [London:John Camden Hotten, 1868]).</p>
                        <p>A poem by James Lindsay Gordon that seems to date from the 1890’s is dedicated to Swinburne; see “A Ballad of the Prince” in <title rendition="#i">Ballads of the Sunlit Years</title> (New York: North American Press, 1904). Gordon’s admiration of Swinburne and Rossetti, I like to think, might have developed from his studies at the College of William and Mary (see Armistead C. Gordon’s sketch in <title rendition="#i">The Library of Southern Literature</title>, ed. Edwin A. Anderson, et al., 17 vols. [Atlanta: Martin and Hoyt Co., 1909], V:1920).</p></item>
                        
                        <item>Letter 157A. p. 80. In the last line, imperfect. <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> imperfect,</item>
                        <item>Letter 192A. p. 100. In note 2 the women are <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> that women are</item>
                        <item>Letter 231B. p. 114. In note 3, Parnell <hi rendition="#u">should
                        be</hi> Purnell</item>
                        <item>Letter 275A. p. 133.  In note 1, April &sb; February</item>
                        <item>Letter 275A. p. 134. To note 2 should be added: <p> Alfred Rosling Bennett in his <title>London and
                                    Londoners in the Eighteen Fifties and Sixties</title> (NY:
                                Adelphi, 1925) offers a description of Menken’s act not, I believe,
                                generally known. Menken, says Bennett, <cit rendition="#blockquote">
                                    <quote>had a good figure, and hid it not under a bushel, but
                                I imagine that the scantiness of her raiment, then something to
                                wonder at, would make no great sensation now. Every night, bound to
                                the raging courser [“really,” he says, “a well-trained tamed
                                steed”], she was galloped over the Steppes at Astley’s—the said
                                Steppes being zig-zagging inclines amongst mountains—at about half
                                a mile an hour, so that the horizon took a long time to reach and
                                patrons had plenty of anatomy for their money</quote>
                                    <bibl>(p. 339).</bibl>
                                </cit>
                        </p>
                            <p>Watts-Dunton reported a remark by Swinburne on Menken that appears not to have been much noticed. He mentioned in a letter to <title>The Times</title> that “some few years before his death I asked Mr. Swinburne what he thought of ‘Infelicia.’ His answer was, ‘Can you ask me? A girl may be admired as ‘Mazeppa’ without being admired as a poet. I think it the greatest rot ever published’” (“Swinburne’s Pamphlets,” <title>The Times</title>, 21 May 1909 p. 8a).</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 309A. p. 164. Stoddard Martin is able to clarify Venturi’s allusion in this letter to what Swinburne had apparently described to her, “the Wagner affair,” “a <hi rendition="#i">screaming</hi> farce”:
                            <quote rendition="#blockquote">
                                I am quite sure that it must be the news that broke in the summer of 1869 about the conductor of the Munich Opera, Hans von Bulow, and his finally agreeing to start divorce proceedings with his wife, the mother of his children, Cosima Liszt (daughter of Franz), who had been living off and on for three years with Wagner, by whom she had had a daughter and recently a son (Siegfried, eventual heir to directorship of the Bayreuth Festival and father of Wolfgang who just gave up same in 2009). What made this more of a sensation was that Bulow was Wagner's favoured conductor and had presided at great pains over first performances of <title>Die Meistersinger</title> in 1868 and was preparing that summer to conduct a command performance of the first part of the Ring for Ludwig II of Bavaria, their patron and paymaster. Ludwig, a covert homosexual, was horrified to learn that his favourite composer had been committing adultery with the wife of his court conductor, not least because the matter had carefully been kept hidden from him. Wagner had troubled his reign since 1865, when he had been banned from Munich by the Cabinet on the grounds that he was using the young king's devotion to his work to set himself up as an all-purpose advisor. The lid came off this boiling pot in the months preceding the exchange between Swinburne and Venturi, and Wagner's many enemies (and friends) were busy stirring it in the press, German, French, what have you.
                            </quote>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 309A. p. 165. In line 12, Mr Holysake <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> Mr Holyoake </item>
                        <item>Letter 309A. p. 165. In note 9 Holyoke <hi rendition="#u">should
                        be</hi> Holyoake</item>
                        
                        <item>Letter 319A. p. 169. In ll. 19-20, “apocryphal” should not be
                            superscript</item>
                        <item>
                            <p>An added letter:</p>
                            
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l321b">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">321B.<hi rendition="#sc">To: John Thomson</hi>
                                        (?)<ref xml:id="ref_01" target="#note_01" rendition="#super">1</ref>
                                    </head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., Jerome McGann</hi>.</head>
                                    <div type="letter">
                                        <opener><dateline rendition="#right">[<date when="1869-11">November
                                                1869?</date>]</dateline></opener>
                                        <p> The Argosy – Vol. 6<ref xml:id="ref_02"
                                                rendition="#super" target="#note_02">2</ref> – was
                                            not received on Wednesday. The parcel directed to Lady
                                            J. Swinburne contained ‘Violet Douglas’<ref
                                                rendition="#super" xml:id="ref_03" target="#note_03"
                                                >3</ref> &amp; ‘The Malay Archipelago’<ref
                                                rendition="#super" xml:id="ref_04" target="#note_04"
                                                >4</ref> Vol. 1<hi rendition="#super #u">st</hi>.
                                            Nothing else was sent but the comic papers, Fraser,
                                            &amp; Templebar.</p>
                                        <p rendition="#ti-10">[a flourish]</p>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_01" rendition="#block  #small">
                                            <ref rendition="#super"
                                                  target="#ref_01">1</ref> I believe Swinburne sent
                                                this note or fragment of a letter (a quarter sheet
                                                of paper torn from a larger sheet) from Holmwood to
                                                John Thomson. It is pasted, Jerome McGann tells me,
                                                to a piece of stiff paper tipped into a book; on the
                                                verso can be discerned a long word not, seemingly,
                                                in Swinburne’s distinctive hand.
                                        </note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_02" rendition="#block #small">
                                            <ref rendition="#super"
                                                  target="#ref_02">2</ref>
                                                <date type="range" from="1868-06" to="1868-12"
                                                  >June-December 1868</date>.
                                        </note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_03" rendition="#block #small">
                                            <ref rendition="#super"
                                                  target="#ref_03">3</ref>
                                                <bibl><author>Emma Marshall</author>, <title>Violet
                                                  Douglas, or the Problems of Life</title>
                                                  (<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <date when="1868"
                                                  >1868</date>)</bibl>.
                                        </note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_04" rendition="#block #small">
                                            <ref rendition="#super"
                                                  target="#ref_04">4</ref>
                                                <bibl><author>Alfred Russel Wallace</author>,
                                                  <title>The Malay Archipelago: The Land of the
                                                  Ourang-utan and The Bird of Paradise: A Narrative
                                                  of Travel with Studies of Man and Nature</title>,
                                                  <extent>2 vols</extent>.
                                                  (<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>:
                                                  <publisher>Macmillan</publisher>, <date
                                                  when="1869">1869</date>)</bibl>.
                                        </note>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 356C. p. 189. In line 9, honor <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> honour </item>
                        <item>
                            Letter 357A. p. 193. To note 7 should be
                                added:
                            <p>To the secondary literature on Swinburne’s sexuality should be added an overlooked essay by Jill Forbes, “Why Did Swinburne Write Flagellation Poems?,” <title>1837-1901: Journalof the Loughborough Victorian Studies Group</title>, no. 2 (October 1977), pp. 21-31.</p>
                        </item>
                      <item>
                        Letter 375A.  p. 191.
                        <p>To note 1 should be added this material concerning John Thomson (and see too the note to Letter 275A), material developed by the English bookseller James Fergusson, material which he has generously allowed me to use even as he is working to develop further information on Thomson.  </p>
                        <p>Mr. Fergusson also sent me a scan of the 1871 census page (see below; used with permission from the National Archives) to which he refers in this description of an item offered in his catalogue <title>Two Magpies: Letters &amp; Papers from the Collections of Jonathan Gili, Christopher Lennox-Boyd &amp; Others</title> (Summer 2013).</p>
                        <figure>
                          <head>
                            Excerpt from James Fergusson's catalogue <title>Two Magpies: Letters &amp; Papers from the Collections of Jonathan Gili, Christopher Lennox-Boyd &amp; Others</title> (Summer 2013).
                          </head>
                          <graphic rendition="#center-block" url="&imgpath;acs0000505-01-003.png"/>
                          <graphic rendition="#center-block" url="&imgpath;acs0000505-01-004.png"/>
                          <graphic rendition="#center-block" url="&imgpath;acs0000505-01-005.png"/>
                        </figure>
                        <figure rendition="#center-block">
                          <head>
                            Page from the 1871 English census, featuring an entry for “Algernon C. Swinburne.” Used with permission of the National Archive.
                          </head>
                          <graphic rendition="#center-block" url="&imgpath;acs0000505-01-006.png"/>
                        </figure>
                      </item>
                      
                          
                        <item>Letter 400A. p. 221. In line 2, favor <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> favour </item>
                        <item>
                            <p rendition="#inline">Letter 400A. p. 221.  I should have been less skeptical of Swinburne’s attending a reading by Robert Buchanan, for I have found a previously unknown account by Will Williams (in 1875 editor of the <title>London Magazine</title>) that suggests Swinburne attended more than one:
                                <cit rendition="#blockquote">
                                    <quote rendition="#block">
                                    I shall never forget seeing him [Swinburne] at the poetic readings given by the poet Buchanan, some years ago, in the Hanover-Square Rooms.   There, in a corner, his intellectual face now wearing a scowl, now a beatific expression, as he was pleased or displeased with his brother poet’s elocution, did he sit twirling his fingers and thumbs in a ludicrously excited way.  Ere long he became the observed of every one.  ‘Who is that?’ whispered a mercantile friend to me, nodding toward him.  ‘That,’ replied I, wishing to surprise the man of figures, ‘is one of our greatest poets, Mr. Swinburne.’  ‘Indeed!’ was the reply, ‘Well, I’ve always heard that poets were a rum lot; now I’ve no doubt about it!’</quote><bibl rendition="#block">(quoted by the American editor and complier William Shepard [Walsh] [1854-1919] in <title>Pen Pictures of Modern Authors</title> [New York: G. P. Putnam’s Sons, 1882], pp. 205-206;  Williams’ account first appeared in <title>Appleton’s Journal</title>, 21 August 1875, p. 252).</bibl>
                                </cit>
                            </p>
                            <p>
                            Though wrong in some biographical details, Shepard recalls Swinburne’s manner and behavior and other details:  “his voice is monotonous, he intones—but it is very earnest. Before the first series of his poems and ballads came out he kept them in a fire-proof box, in loose sheets, and plunging his arm in up to his elbow, used to bring out his favorites.” Shepard mentions that “Anactoria” was known in manuscript among Swinburne’s friends as “Sappho”: “we did not think that he would ever dare to publish this poem with ‘Dolores,’ ‘The Leper,’ etc.” (pp. 203-204).      
                            </p>
                            <p>
                            Shepard includes another anecdote Williams quotes from the London correspondent of a provincial newspaper.  The correspondent recounts at some length Swinburne’s brilliant performance at a dinner hosted by a lady to whom the poet at the end of the evening inscribed a copy of his poems.  Then three days later he reappeared and apologized, having no recollection of the evening and thinking he had missed it: “he had mislaid the card—he had mistaken the night—he had had to go down into the country.”  Shepard also tells of Swinburne’s taking a footstool to a public banquet honoring Browning: “he insisted on placing [the footstool] at the master’s feet and solemnly seating himself thereon.”  Browning is said to have “a warm liking for Swinburne,” but is also supposed to have cautioned him: “‘You foolish boy!’ he is represented as saying to him on one occasion, with a playful shake of the finger, ‘what do you mean by prostituting such splendid genius?’”  Shepard concludes by quoting from the account of Swinburne by Louisa Chandler Moulton which she published in February 1878 in <title>Lippincott’s Monthly Magazine</title>.	</p>
                            
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 419A. p. 231 In line 1, to you For <hi rendition="#u">should
                            be</hi> to you. For </item>
                        <item>Letter 422A. p. 233. In the second line of para 1, lend <hi
                                rendition="#u">seems more likely to be</hi> send</item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            <floatingText xml:id="l450a" rendition="#textbox">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">450A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Ford Madox Brown</hi></head>
                            <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., South African National Gallery</hi>.<ref target="#note_12" xml:id="ref_12" rendition="#super">1</ref></head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <dateline rendition="#center">
                                                Holmwood,<lb/>
                                                Shiplake,<lb/>
                                                Henley on Thames.
                                            </dateline>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right"><date when="1872-12-14">Dec. 14th [1872]</date></dateline>
                                            <salute>My dear Brown</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">
                                        As it is first of all &amp; most of all to your kindness &amp; friendship that I owe the good fortune which has come to me I cannot but write at once to tell &amp; thank you.  Mr. Watts writes me word<ref rendition="#super" xml:id="ref_13" target="#note_13">2</ref> that Chapman &amp; Hall offer &lt;mo [?]&gt; on most liberal terms to buy out Hotten, &amp; having invested in my works to issue them in a cheap edition, such as theirs of Carlyle, which it will match.   This Chapman expects to sell ‘by thousands’ &amp; (says Watts) ‘will pay me for most liberally.’  It is the very thing &amp; the very firm [?] I would have chosen.
                                        </p>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">
                                            Even you never did a kinder thing for any of your friends than when you brought me acquainted with Watts.  I wish I had any means of shewing my gratitude.  Had it been Jowett instead of Dean Stanley<ref rendition="#super" target="#note_14" xml:id="ref_14">3</ref> whom Cambridge had complimented by a nomination as ‘select preacher’ (but they won’t do that in a hurry, J being in all Christian eyes the real ‘heresiarch’ &amp; son of perdition,<ref rendition="#super" target="#note_15" xml:id="ref_15">4</ref> by the side of whose black infidelity the ‘rationalism’ of Stanley is white, or at least ma[u]ve[?]-colour) I might have a friend at court there which <choice><abbr>w<hi rendition="#super">d</hi></abbr><expan>would</expan></choice> perhaps be of some service.   As it is, I can only send my sincerest hopes that your election<ref target="#note_16" rendition="#super" xml:id="ref_16">5</ref> may prosper in that quarter--&amp; remain in haste,</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-15">Ever yours most sincerely</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-17 #i">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                        <postscript>
                                            <p rendition="#indent">And what a day of judgment &amp; ‘the great jubilation’ it will be for British Virtue when I shall stalk triumphant over the land in a cheap edition sowing broadcast the seeds of immorality, atheism, &amp; &lt;illeg.> revolution!</p></postscript>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_12" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref12" rendition="#super">1</ref> I am grateful to Jerome McGann for sending me copies of the three Swinburne letters he found at the South African National Gallery and to Marilyn Martin at the Gallery for permission to publish them.</note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_13" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref13" rendition="#super">2</ref> Watts-Dunton’s letter is no. 447C, in <title>Uncollected Letters</title>.</note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_14" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref14" rendition="#super">3</ref> Arthur Penrhyn Stanley (1815-1881), installed in 1864 as Dean of Westminster Abbey, was at this time one of the select preachers at Cambridge and was to preach there in January and February 1873 (<title>The Times</title>, 10 December 1872, p. 8b).  But Swinburne seems to be alluding as well to a controversy about Stanley’s nomination to be a select preacher at Oxford, which occasioned some opposition by members of Convocation.  See the exchange of letters in <title>The Times</title> (7 December 1872, p.  10c), where Stanley is accused of being a patron to a Unitarian teacher and to an infidel as well as being “the avowed champion of a negative and cloudy Christianity which is really preparing the way for the rejection of all revealed truth.”</note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_15"  rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_15" rendition="#super">4</ref> John 17:12; 2 Thessalonians 2:3.</note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_16" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_16" rendition="#super">5</ref> Brown had “applied for the Slade professorship at Cambridge, claiming that a practicing artist, rather than a connoisseur, should hold this post” (<title>ODNB</title>).</note>
                                            
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        
                      <item>
                        <p>An added letter:</p>
                        
                        <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l490a">
                          <index indexName="nav"/>
                          <body>
                            <head rendition="#plainhead">490A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: John Thomson</hi><!-- <ref xml:id="ref_01" target="#note_01" rendition="#super">1</ref> --></head>
                            <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: Facsimile in Thomas Catling, <title>My Life’s Pilgrimage</title> (London, John Murray, 1911), p. [123]</hi>.</head>
                            <div type="letter">
                              <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                  <placeName rendition="#block">Holmwood</placeName>
                                  <date rendition="#block" when="1873-11-25">Nov. 25th [1873]<ref xml:id="ref_61" target="#note_61" rendition="#super">1</ref></date>
                                </dateline>
                                <salute>Dear John,</salute>
                              </opener>
                              <!-- body -->
                              <list type="ordered">
                                <item>The similitude of Shakespeare to the sea forms the overture of Victor Hugo’s book—“William Shakespeare”—pp 15, 16 (ed.1864).<ref xml:id="ref_62" target="#note_62" rendition="#super">2</ref></item> 
                                <item>The license of using a singular verb &lt;illeg.> after two substantives (as in the verses you quote) has always been admitted, I think, in modern English verse. Of course it is a license to say ‘the flower-dust &amp; the flower-smell clings’<ref xml:id="ref_63" target="#note_63" rendition="#super">3</ref> but even if unpardonable the offender will find himself chastised in good company.</item>
                              </list>
                              
                              <closer>
                                <salute xml:lang="fr" rendition="#ti-12">Mille amitiés,</salute>
                                <salute rendition="#ti-13">Yours ever</salute>
                                <signed rendition="#ti-14">A C Swinburne</signed>
                              </closer>
                            </div>
                            <div type="notes">
                              <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                              <note xml:id="note_61" rendition="#block  #small">
                                <p><ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_61">1</ref> The year is a guess, based on Catling’s nearby account, apparently around Christmas 1873, of John Thomson’s dropping by Catling’s office one noon in search of a drink (he settled on champagne, disappointed that no whisky was available).  Catling notes of this letter that Thomson “had undertaken to make inquiry for me as to Victor Hugo’s comparison of Shakspere to the sea, and had added a little criticism on his own account, which brought forth Swinburne’s defence” (p. 122).</p>
                                <p>Catling includes in his memoir an account of a luncheon at The Pines in July 1899.  He and W. E. Church arrived at 1:30 p.m., as directed.  The goal of the negotiations with Watts-Dunton was to obtain a poem for publication in the paper Catling edited, <title>Lloyd’s Weekly News</title>: “any idea of asking the poet to write was out of the question; some compositions, however, were admitted to exist in manuscript, and it was thought that Mr. Swinburne might be induced to revise one for publication in the way desired.”  Swinburne is described as returning from his “usual morning walk”:<cit rendition="#blockquote">
                                  <quote>Suddenly the outer door opened and the poet came bounding into the hall, with a noisy bustle which seemed to be understood as an indication that he was ready for lunch.  In a very few minutes the meal was on the table, and after a cordial greeting the party of four sat down.  Mr. Swinburne’s bearing was marked by a simplicity which rightly belongs to a man in his own home.  If conversation languished to some extent it was by reason of the afflicting deafness under which the poet laboured.  Having finished his bottle of beer, he turned from the table to some new books which had come in that day.  A marvelous change came over him; all seriousness instantly disappeared.  One volume, which had been eagerly expected, contained references to the poet’s schooldays.  As he raised his head and pointed these out to Mr. Watts-Dunton, the flashing eyes and exalted expression made him appear as one transformed.</quote>
                                  <bibl>(pp, 276-277)</bibl>
                                </cit>
                                  Catlling notes that “the poem never came to hand.”</p>  
                                <p>As to what book led to Swinburne’s transformation, I am not sure since the ones published in 1899 seem not to mention Swinburne directly.  My guess, though, is Albert Lubbock, <title>Memories of Eton and Etonians</title> (London: John Murray), which was reviewed in the <title>Athenaeum</title> in the issue of June 24, 1899 (p. 775) and which features an illustration (between pp. 170 and 171), from <title>Vanity Fair</title>, of Swinburne’s tutor, the Rev. James L. Joynes, with a birch and the flogging block.</p>
                                <p>I am indebted to Clive Simmonds, Cambridge University Library, for bringing this letter and letters 809B and 1739B, below, to my attention, and for his work towards the annotations.</p>
                                <!-- note body -->
                              </note>
                              <note xml:id="note_62" rendition="#block  #small">
                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_62">2</ref>Paris: Librairie Internationale, 1864.
                              </note>
                              <note xml:id="note_63" rendition="#block  #small">
                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_63">3</ref>“The End of A Month,” <title>Dark Blue</title>, April 1871, p. 220, illustrated by Simeon Solomon, re-titled as “At a Month’s End” and collected in <title>PBII</title> (1878), where the line reads, “The flower-dust with the flower smell clings,” perhaps a result of Thomson’s query. 
                                
                              </note>
                            </div>
                          </body>
                        </floatingText>
                      </item>
                      <item>Letter 524B. p. 319. Twice in the middle of the page, Checque <hi
                                rendition="#u">should be</hi> Cheque</item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            
                            <floatingText xml:id="l535a" rendition="#textbox">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">535A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Ford Madox Brown</hi></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., South African National Gallery</hi>.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <dateline rendition="#center">
                                                The Orchard<lb/>
                                                Niton<lb/>
                                                Isle of Wight</dateline>
                                            <dateline rendition="#center">
                                                <date when="1874-07-17">July 17th [1874]</date>
                                            </dateline>
                                            <salute>My dear Brown</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">	I was very sorry to leave London without seeing you again if only to make my apologies, &amp; express my regret for having been unable to attend either of your evenings, not being well enough at the time to go out to parties.  I am very glad to hear that Hueffer’s projected book<ref xml:id="ref_17" rendition="#super" target="#note_17">1</ref> is to appear under Chatto’s auspices, &amp; should be more so if I <choice><abbr>c<hi rendition="#super #u">d</hi></abbr><expan>could</expan></choice> flatter myself with the hope that I might have been of any service in the matter.</p>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">	With regard to the adaptation of Bothwell to the stage, I had an interview by appointment with Watts the day before I left town, when I told him that he was fully authorized to make any arrangements with Mr. Oxenford<ref xml:id="ref_18" rendition="#super" target="#note_18">2</ref> in my name that he might think best.  If on this understanding you, he, &amp; Mr. O. can come to any conclusion, tant mieux.  I don’t see, &lt;that> having so thoroughly reliable a delegate, that my presence <choice><abbr>w<hi rendition="#super">d</hi></abbr><expan>would</expan></choice> further or that my absence need impede a satisfactory settlement.  I shall be here (Diabolo volente) for the next two months or so.  It <choice><abbr>w<hi rendition="#super">d</hi></abbr><expan>would</expan></choice> give me great pleasure to see myself on the boards &amp; Mrs. Bell<ref xml:id="ref_19" rendition="#super" target="#note_19">3</ref> as my Queen; the only stipulation I told Watts I <choice><abbr>sh<hi rendition="#super #u">d</hi></abbr><expan>should</expan></choice> make as to the adaptation (in which he fully concurred) was that nothing <choice><abbr>sh<hi rendition="#super #u">d</hi></abbr><expan>should</expan></choice> be interpolated or retouched by any hand but mine; the adapter being of course free to use at his own fullest discretion the powers of excision &amp; selection.  The practical part of the business, as to division of profits &amp;c, I leave of course in Watt’s hands with the fullest confidence.<ref xml:id="ref_20" rendition="#super" target="#note_20">4</ref></p>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">I have just read Quatrevingt Treize—it is simply a divine work, &amp; your remarks on it exactly expressed my own present feelings.  V. H. has written me a quite overwhelming note of thanks &amp; praise for the dedicatory sonnet of Bothwell.</p>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">When you see Forbes Robertson<ref xml:id="ref_21" rendition="#super" target="#note_21">5</ref> please tell him I only received this morning his note of the 6th inviting me to meet you at his house, which had I been in town I should have been delighted to do.</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-15">Ever yours</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-17 #i">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_17" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_17" rendition="#super">1</ref> Possibly <title>Richard Wagner and the Music of the Future</title> (London: Chapman and Hall, 1874), by Francis Hueffer (1845-1889), the music critic and, from 1872, the son-in-law of Brown.</note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_18" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_18" rendition="#super">2</ref> John Oxenford (1812-1877), playwright and translator.</note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_19" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_19" rendition="#super">3</ref>Unidentified beyond being “the aspirant Mary Stuart” (<title>Letters</title>, II, 313).</note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_20" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_20" rendition="#super">4</ref> This entire sentence is interlined after “selection.”</note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_21" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_21" rendition="#super">5</ref> Johnston Forbes-Robertson (1853-1937).  Having studied at the Royal Academy (and sat to Rossetti and Brown), Forbes-Robertson had just started his illustrious acting career, his first part being, in March, in <title>Mary Stuart</title>, by W. G. Willis (<title>ODNB</title>).  In his<title> A Player Under Three Reigns</title> (1925; rpt. New York: Benjamin Blom, 1971), Forbes-Robertson describes Swinburne’s appearance and “youthful enthusiasm,” his delight at a kitten with “‘the grace of a thousand virgins,’” his being “very excited on one glass of claret,” his soothing a child, and his readings, especially one of <title>Atalanta in Calydon</title> “in a sort of chant” just before it was published (pp. 43-45).</note>
                                        
                                    </div>

                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 562A. p. 330. In note 2, F. C. <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> E. C.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="mi2">
                    <index indexName="nav"/>
                    <head rendition="#center #styled">Vol. II.—The More Important</head>
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>
                            <!-- fix formatting of letter -->
                            <p>An added letter: </p>
                            
                            <floatingText xml:id="l563a" rendition="#textbox">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                <head rendition="#plainhead">563A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: A. C. Swinburne,
                                    from Anne Benson Proctor</hi><ref rendition="#super"
                                        xml:id="ref_05" target="#note_05">1</ref></head>
                                <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., Terry L.
                                Meyers</hi>.</head>
                                <div><opener>
                                            <seg rendition="#center">[mourning stationery]</seg>
                                            <dateline rendition="#center #i">
                                                <date when="1874-10-18">Oct 18<hi rendition="#super">th.</hi> 1874</date>
                                            </dateline>
                                            <address rendition="#center"><addrLine>32 Weymouth St.</addrLine><addrLine>Portland Place W</addrLine></address>
                                            <salute>My dear M<hi rendition="#super">r</hi>
                                            Swinburne</salute>
                                        </opener><p rendition="#indent"> I find on again looking at your charming tribute to my
                                            dear husband that it ought to be dated the 4<hi rendition="#super">th</hi> instead of the 5<hi rendition="#super">th</hi>. <ref rendition="#super" xml:id="ref_06" target="#note_06">2</ref>
                                        </p><p rendition="#indent"> I cannot tell you what a pleasure your good company was
                                            to me, how you lifted me out of all that has been
                                            pressed upon me for the last fortnight—</p> 
                                            <p rendition="#indent">With my Poet,
                                            all that was highest seemed to have gone—and left a
                                            woman whose whole time &amp; thoughts were engaged
                                            by Lawyers, Rents, Lodgings &amp;c— </p><p rendition="#indent"> You said some words about taking up my time— had I not
                                            been obliged to go out, I should not have parted with
                                            you.— </p><closer rendition="#ti-4">
                                            <salute>Your grateful old <hi rendition="#super #x-small">fd.</hi></salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#i">
                                                <name>Anne B. Procter</name>
                                            </signed>
                                        </closer></div><div type="notes"><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/><note xml:id="note_05" rendition="#block #small">
                                            <p><ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_05">1</ref> (1799-1888), wife of Bryan Waller Proctor
                                                (Barry Cornwall) and mother of Adelaide Anne
                                                Proctor. The copy of her pamphlet <title>Letters
                                                  Addressed to Mrs. Basil Montagu and B. W.
                                                  Proctor by Mr. Thomas Carlyle</title> ([London]:
                                                printed for private circulation, [1881]), inscribed
                                                in her hand “A. C. Swinburne,” is in my collection
                                                (see <title>Letters</title>, IV, 209-210).</p>
                                        </note><note xml:id="note_06" rendition="#block #small">
                                            <p><ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_06">2</ref> Swinburne marked the death on 4 October of
                                                Procter with “In Memory of Barry Cornwall” (see,
                                                above, Letter 562A, note).</p>
                                        </note></div></body></floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 598A. p. 9. To note 1 might be added: <p>
                            To Swinburne’s attendance in the Reading Room of the British Museum, two further witnesses might be adduced, both in his later years.   Laurence Binyon (1869-1943) recalled seeing Swinburne at work:<cit rendition="#blockquote"><quote>
                            … he had seen him once in the flesh.  It was in the British Museum Reading Room, which Swinburne used to visit from time to time to consult the editions of the Elizabethan dramatists.  There he would indulge in his gift of picturesque blasphemy and vituperation at the expense of the commentators of the play he was studying or at the expense of some neighbouring reader who was annoying him—and, being stone deaf, he imagined he was unheard.</quote> <bibl>
                            (“The Swinburne Centenary: Mr. Laurence Binyon’s Appreciation,” <title>The Times</title>, 5 May 1937, p. 14c)</bibl>
                            </cit>
                            John Masefield (1878-1967) told a similar story:
                            <cit rendition="#blockquote">
                                <quote>
                            Then there [at the Reading Room] was that great figure Algernon Charles Swinburne.  He was very deaf and was brought there by Mr. Watts-Dunton and set down at a table, while everyone in the room looked at him.   Watts-Dunton shouted in a loud voice: ‘I will come back at one o’clock to take you out to lunch,’ and Swinburne then settled down to read.  Being deaf he did not realize what an amount of noise he sometimes made, and from time to time indignant readers turned around to protest, but when they saw it was Mr. Swinburne they took no further notice.</quote> <bibl>
                            (“Mr. Masefield on His Early Reading,” <title>The Times</title>, 9 July 1936, p. 19g)</bibl>
                            </cit>
                        </p>
                        </item>
                        
                            
                        <item>Letter 634C. p. 24. The mention of Swinburne’s letter should have a
                            note: See <title>Letters</title>, III, 34-35.</item>
                        <item>Letter 663B. p. 30. The first sheet of writing paper is headed
                            “Holmwood, / Shiplake, / Henley on Thames.”</item>
                        <item>Letter 668B. p. 40. In line 1, checque <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> cheque</item>
                        <item>Letter 680A. p. 45. In line 2, ________ <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> ____ _____</item>
                        <item>Letter 685A. p. 52. In line 8, the two verticals should be
                        immediately beneath the two c’s</item>
                        <item>Letter 702A. p. 59. In note 5, [1877] should follow 1878</item>
                      <item>
                        Letter 709A. p. 65. The first three sentences of this letter, slightly reworked, appear in Pfeiffer’s <title>Sonnets</title>, ed. J. Edward Pfeiffer, (London: Field &amp; Tuer, 1886), p. vi.
                        
                        <ref type="hathitrust_embed" target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/pst.000006243463?urlappend=%3Bui=embed%3Bseq=14">Pfeiffer's <title>Sonnets</title>, ed. J. Edward Pfeiffer, (London: Field &amp; Tuer, 1886). Retrieved from the HathiTrust Digital Library at <ptr target="http://hdl.handle.net/2027/pst.000006243463"/></ref>
                      </item>
                        <item>Letter 830C. p. 112. In line 13, <hi rendition="#i">metaphyical</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#i">metaphysical</hi></item>
                      <item>
                        <p>An added letter:</p>
                        
                        <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l890b">
                          <index indexName="nav"/>
                          <body>
                            <head rendition="#plainhead">890B. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Eugène Joël</hi><ref xml:id="ref_81" target="#note_81" rendition="#super">1</ref>
                              <!-- <ref xml:id="ref_01" target="#note_01" rendition="#super">1</ref>-->
                            </head>
                            <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: Printed in <title>The Leicester Chronicle and the Leicestershire Mercury</title>, <date when="1877-12-15">December 15, 1877</date>, p. 12.</hi></head>
                            <div type="letter">
                              <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right"><placeName>3, Great James-street<lb/>Bedford-row<lb/>London, W.C.</placeName></dateline>
                              </opener>
                              <p xml:lang="fr">Monsieur, — Agréez mes remerciments bien sincères des beaux et puissants vers que vous avez bien voulu me dédier, et des paroles cordiales et sympathiques qui les accompagnent et que je n’ai reçues que ce soir même—c'est à dire quatre ou cinq jours “après date”—mais qui suffiraient presque à mêler un bon souvenir aux souvenirs exécrables de cette date maudite, le 2 Décembre lui-même.</p>  
                              
                              <closer>
                                <signed rendition="#right">Algernon Ch. Swinburne.</signed>
                                <dateline xml:lang="fr"><date when="1877-12-09">9 Décembre, 1877.</date></dateline>
                              </closer>
                            </div>
                            <div type="notes">
                              <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                              <note xml:id="note_81" rendition="#block  #small">
                                <p><ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_81">1</ref>Sometime Master of Modern Languages, Clifton College, and editor of various textbooks; later Professor of French at Mason Science College, Birmingham.</p>
                                <p>The editor of the <title>Leicester Chronicle and the Leicestershire Mercury</title> introduces Swinburne’s letter with this comment:  
                                  <cit rendition="#blockquote"><quote>The French poem on the anniversary of the 2nd December [the coup d’état of Napoleon III in 1851], written by our townsman, M. Eugene Joel, and published in our issue of the 1st inst. [p. 2] was, as our readers will remember dedicated to the eminent poet, Mr. Algernon C.  Swinburne. [“Original French Poems. IV. L’Anniversaire.  2 Décembre, 1851.  A L’Illustre Algernon Swinburne”].  That gentleman has written to M. Joel, thanking him for his ‘fine and vigorous verses’ and expressing sympathy with the sentiments of the poem.  We have been favoured with a perusal of the letter, of which the following is a copy.</quote>
                                  </cit>
                                </p>
                                
                                <!-- note body -->
                              </note>
                            </div>
                          </body>
                        </floatingText>
                      </item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                        <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l897a">
                            <index indexName="nav"/>
                            <body>
                                <head rendition="#plainhead">897A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: William Michael Rossetti</hi></head>
                                <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., South African National Gallery</hi>.</head>
                                <div>
                                    <opener>
                                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                                           <address>
                                               <addrLine>3 Gr Jas St</addrLine>
                                           </address>
                                        </dateline>
                                        <dateline rendition="#right">
                                           <date when="1878-01-17">Janry 17<hi rendition="#super">th</hi> [1878]</date>
                                        </dateline>
                                        <salute>Dear Rossetti</salute>
                                    </opener>
                                    <p rendition="#indent">I trouble you with one line to beg one word <add place="above">⁁by return of post</add> in answer to the question whether in your ed<hi rendition="#super #u">n</hi> of Shelley<ref target="#note_22" xml:id="ref_22" rendition="#super">1</ref> you had or had not a note on the ‘Numidian seps’ (Prom. Unbound, Act III, Sc.1) giving a reference to the passage in Lucan alluded to.   There is no such note in Forman’s ed<hi rendition="#super #u">n</hi>;<ref rendition="#super" target="#note_23" xml:id="ref_23">2</ref> &amp; believing (what I now feel less sure of) that there was none in yours, my copy of which is at Holmwood, I have written to the Athenaeum announcing as my own the discovery of this rather eccentric &amp; &lt;illeg.> <add place="above">⁁incongruous</add> reference on the part of the Almighty tyrant.  Let me know at once <add place="above">⁁if</add> I have wronged you, that my note may be withdrawn in time before next week.<ref rendition="#super" target="#note_24" xml:id="ref_24">3</ref></p>
                                    <closer>
                                        <salute rendition="#ti-15">Ever yours</salute>
                                        <signed rendition="#ti-17 #i">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                    </closer>
                                </div>
                                <div type="notes">
                                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                    <note xml:id="note_22" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_22" rendition="#super">1</ref><title>The Complete Poetical Works of Percy Bysshe Shelley</title>, 3 vols. (London: E. Moxon, 1878).</note>
                                    <note xml:id="note_23" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_23" rendition="#super">2</ref><title>The Poetical Works of Percy Bysshe Shelley</title>, ed. Harry Buxton Forman, 4 vols. (London: Reeves &amp; Turner, 1876, 1877).</note>
                                    <note xml:id="note_24" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_24" rendition="#super">3</ref> Swinburne’s note appeared in the issue of 9 February 1878 (Letters, IV, 42-43).</note>
                                </div>
                            </body>
                        </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 903C. p. 145. In note 1, 1877 <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> 1878</item>
                        <item>Letter 930A. p. 167. In line 9, [21] <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> [’]</item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l980b">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                <head rendition="#plainhead">980B. <hi rendition="#sc">To: A Book
                                    Seller</hi></head>
                                <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., Terry L.
                                    Meyers</hi>.</head><div><opener>
                                            <address ><addrLine rend="margin-bottom:0;margin-left:15em;">The Pines,</addrLine><addrLine rend="margin-bottom:0;margin-left:17em">Putney Hill. S. W.</addrLine></address>
                                            <dateline rend="margin-top:0;margin-left:17em;">
                                                <date> Nov. 24<hi rendition="#super #u">th</hi> 1879</date>
                                            </dateline>
                                            <salute>Sir</salute>
                                        </opener><p rendition="#indent"> I shall be obliged if you can send me the copy of
                                            Marvell’s Works marked in the accompanying leaf from
                                            your catalogue.<ref rendition="#super" xml:id="ref_07" target="#note_07">1</ref></p><closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-9">I am, etc.</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-10">A. C. Swinburne</signed>
                                            </closer></div><div type="notes"><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/><note xml:id="note_07" rendition="#block #small">
                                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_07">1</ref> Without the leaf, identifying which
                                                edition of Andrew Marvell’s works was on offer is
                                                impossible. It seems likely to have been an earlier
                                                edition than the one in Swinburne’s library at his
                                                death, <title>Complete Works in Verse and
                                                Prose</title>, ed. A. B. Grosart (printed for
                                                private circulation: 1872-1875) (lot 493 in <title>A
                                                  Catalogue of the Library of Algernon Charles
                                                  Swinburne</title>).
                                        </note></div></body></floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1001B. p. 206. In line 4, <hi rendition="#i">favourite</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#i">favorite</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1055A. p. 246. In note 2, Landon <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> Landor</item>
                        <item>Letter 1070B. p. 262. In line 3, honored <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> honoured</item>
                        <item>Letter 1070B. p. 262. In line 22, I must abhor <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> I most abhor</item>
                        <item>Letter 1081A. p. 265. In line 11, Carlyles’ <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> Carlyle’s</item>
                        <item>Letter 1096A. p. 274. In note 1, bottomless, <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> bottomless.</item>
                        <item>
                            Letter 1096A. p. 274. In the footnote, the
                                reference to “several versions” of Swinburne’s squib on Wilde might
                                have been more expansive:
                            <p> In 1974 or 1975, John Mayfield directed my
                                attention to two issues of the Foyles Bookshop magazine,
                                    <title>Foylibra</title>. In a review of <title>The Trials of
                                    Oscar Wilde</title> by H. Montgomery Hyde (August 1974, p. 35),
                                Edgar Lustgarten quoted lines about Wilde that he understood were by
                                T. W. H. Crosland:
                                <quote rendition="#blockquote #nq">
                                <lg><l>Earth to earth</l><l>And sod to sod</l><l>No wonder the Almighty God</l><l>Made the pit</l><l>Bottomless.</l></lg>
                            </quote>
                            </p>
                            <p> In the issue for November 1974 (p. 5), several
                                correspondents linked the lines to Swinburne and offered variants.
                                Gerald Hull thought the squib should read,
                                <quote rendition="#blockquote #nq">
                                <lg><l>When Oscar came to join his God,</l><l>Not earth, but sod.</l><l>It was for sinners such as this</l><l>Hell was created bottomless.</l></lg>
                                </quote>
                                </p>
                                <p>
                                Jeremy Smith cited the lines as I quote them from the George Macbeth
                                anthology of <title>Victorian Verse</title> and located them,
                                attributed to Swinburne, in the <title>Silver Treasury of Light
                                    Verse</title>, edited by Oscar Williams (1957).</p>
                            <p> My conviction that the squib is by Swinburne is
                                based on its similarity in wit and homophobia to his squibs about
                                John Addington Symonds (see note 1 to Letter 446A, above), but, as I
                                said in CBEL3, “evidence is wanting.” </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1123a">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">1123A. To: Rev. Canon Frederick Langbridge</hi><ref xml:id="ref_31"
                                        rendition="#super" target="#note_031">1</ref></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">
                                        <hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., Terry L. Meyers.</hi>
                                    </head><div><opener>
                                        
                                        <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                                    </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">Thanks for the gift of your volume.<ref xml:id="ref_32"
                                            rendition="#super" target="#note_032">2</ref> I have taken measures to get your letter to Mr Morris duly forwarded to his present direction.</p>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">I should not wish any one of my ‘Christmas Antipones’<ref xml:id="ref_33"
                                            rendition="#super" target="#note_033">3</ref> to appear separately from the others; &amp; &lt;as> [?] I presume you would hardly wish to reprint the three as they stand.</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-18">Yours very truly</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-21">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                            
                                        </closer></div><div type="notes"><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/><note xml:id="note_31" rendition="#block #small">
                                            <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_31">1</ref>See <title>Uncollected Letters</title>, II, 316n.  The envelope is addressed in Swinburne’s hand “The Rev. F. Langbridge / Wellesley Lodge / Limerick”; the postmarks are Putney, January 12, 1882 and Limerick January 13, 1882. 
                                        </note><note xml:id="note_32" rendition="#block #small">
                                            <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_32">2</ref> Unidentified.</note>
                                            <note xml:id="note_33" rendition="#block #small">
                                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_33">3</ref> From <title>Songs before Sunrise</title> (1871).
                                            </note></div></body></floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1124c">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1124C. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Oswald John Simon</hi><ref target="#note_28" xml:id="ref_30" rendition="#super">1</ref></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: George A. Yates, “The Centenary of Swinburne.  An Oxford Letter.  Persecution of Jews in Russia,” <title>The Times</title>, 10 April 1937, p. 15f.</hi></head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <address>
                                               <addrLine rend="margin-left:20em;">The Pines,</addrLine>
<addrLine rend="margin-left:20em;">Putney Hill, S.W.</addrLine>
                        </address>
                                            <dateline rend="margin-left:20em;margin-top:1em;"><date when="1882-01-31">January 31, 1882</date>
                                            </dateline>
                                            <salute>Dear Sir,</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">I need not assure you of my cordial sympathy with your projected movement: but having no sort of connexion, direct or indirect, with the University which I left more than 20 years since without taking a degree, I think that my signature to an address intended for its Vice-Chancellor would scarcely be proper in itself and could certainly be of little or no service to a design which has no heartier well-wisher than</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-17">Yours very truly,</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-19">A. C. Swinburne</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <note xml:id="note_28" rendition="#block #small">
                                            <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/><p><ref target="#ref_30" rendition="#super">1</ref>Yates identifies the recipient of this letter as Oswald John Simon (1855-1932), author, community worker, and founder of the Maccabaeans. Simon, who had studied at Balliol, perhaps wrote Swinburne at the instigation of his father, Sir John Simon (1818-1897, on whom see the <title>ODNB</title>). Yates suggests Swinburne is replying to an appeal to sign one of several addresses protesting the treatment of Jews in Russia, most likely an Oxford occasion. Serjeant Simon’s involvement is recounted in the <title>Jewish Encyclopedia</title> (see <ref target="http://www.jewishencyclopedia.com/">www.jewishencyclopedia.com</ref>): “When the knowledge reached England of the persecution of the Jews in Russia in 1881 and 1882 Simon conceived and carried into effect the idea of securing a protest from the entire English people. Within three weeks he had so aroused the feelings of the public men to whom he had personally submitted the issues, that a requisition, signed by the highest representatives in England, was presented to the lord mayor; and a meeting was convened on Feb. 1, 1882.”</p>
                                            <p>Swinburne’s <ref target="http://www.purl.org/swinburnearchive/acs0000001-05-i084.xml">“On the Russian Persecution of the Jews”</ref> (collected in <title>TLOP</title> [1882]) had just appeared in <title>The Daily Telegraph</title>, 25 January 1882.</p>
                                        </note>
                                        
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                           
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1155a">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1155A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: ?</hi></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: An Unidentified Auction Clipping, Terry L. Meyers</hi>.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <dateline rendition="#center">
                                                The Pines,<lb/>
                                                Putney Hill.<lb/>
                                                S.W.
                                            </dateline>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right"><date when="1882-06-12">July 12, 82</date>.</dateline>
                                            <salute>Sir</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">I am obliged to you for sending me the newspaper cutting just received from London, &amp; remain</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-15">Yours truly</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-15 #i">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1195B. p. 313. Note 2 should be expanded: See too my review of
                            Henderson, <title>JEGP</title>, 75 (July 1976), 456-8.</item>
                      <item>An added letter:
                        
                        <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1197a">
                          <index indexName="nav"/>
                          <body>
                            <head rendition="#plainhead">1197A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: T. Hall Caine</hi></head>
                            <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: T. Hall Caine, <title>Cobwebs of Criticism: A Review of the First Reviewers of the ‘Lake,’ ‘Satanic,’ and ‘Cockney’ Schools</title> (London: Elliot Stock, 1883), pp. 136n-137n.
                            </hi>.<ref xml:id="ref_51" rendition="#super" target="#note_51">1</ref></head>
                            <div>
                              <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                  <date when="1882-11" rendition="#sc">[November 1882?]<ref xml:id="ref_52" rendition="#super" target="#note_52">2</ref></date>
                                </dateline>
                              </opener>
                              <p>The cruel injustice you have—of course unwittingly—done to the memory of Leigh Hunt is no matter of opinion; it is one of fact and evidence. So far from attempting no defence of Keats, in 1820 he published, on the appearance of the “Lamia and other Poems” in that year, perhaps the most cordial, generous and enthusiastic tribute of affectionate and ardent praise that had ever been offered by a poet to a poet, in the shape of a review almost overflowing the limits of the magazine in which it appeared (the <title>Indicator</title><ref xml:id="ref_53" rendition="#super" target="#note_53">3</ref>). A more “loud and earnest defence of Keats”<ref xml:id="ref_54" rendition="#super" target="#note_54">4</ref> could not be imagined or desired. And if Keats ever forgot this, or ever expressed doubts of Hunt's loyal and devoted regard, it simply shows that Keats was himself a disloyal and thankless man of genius, as utterly unworthy as he was utterly incapable of grateful, and unselfish, and manly friendship.</p>
                              
                            </div>
                            <div type="notes"><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/><note xml:id="note_51" rendition="#block #small">
                              <p><ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_51">1</ref>Caine introduces this excerpt as from “an eminent poet” who objected to Caine’s “so-called impeachment” of Leigh Hunt in <title>Recollections of Dante Gabriel Rossetti</title> (London: Eliot Stock, 1882).  Caine there expressed his disdain for Hunt’s having “attempted no defence of Keats when the bread was being taken out his mouth” by hostile reviewers (p. 177).</p>
             <p>That the poet being quoted is Swinburne I deduce from Swinburne’s sustained admiration of Hunt and from two marginalia in a copy of <title>Cobwebs of Criticism</title> I have acquired for my collection.  That copy has a bookplate, “From the Library of Walter Theodore Watts-Dunton,” and is inscribed in pencil on the inside front cover, “MS notes by Swinburne.”</p>  <p>I believe that the marginalia and under-linings are indeed by Swinburne and in this particular instance point to his being the author of the letter Caine quotes.  I incorporate in the text above two corrections that, I think, could have been made only by the person who actually wrote the letter.  One correction shifts a comma from after “in 1820” to before it, and the other changes “thankless son” to “thankless man.”  In the rest of the note, where Caine defends his view, Swinburne has put in the right margin marks akin to ticks to the last four of Caine’s points.</p> 
                                <p>To Swinburne’s expressions of admiration for Hunt might be added a comment he made <foreign xml:lang="it" rendition="#i">vivâ voce</foreign> to Harry Buxton Forman and recorded in a note to stanza 35 of “Adonais” where Forman recounts his survey as to who Shelley had in mind among the mourners as the “gentlest among the wise”: said Swinburne, “there is not the slightest doubt it was Leigh Hunt” (see <title>The Works of Percy Bysshe Shelley in Verse and Prose</title>, 8 vols. [London: Reeves and Turner, 1880], III, 22n).</p>
                            </note>
                              <note xml:id="note_52" rendition="#block #small">
                               <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_52">2</ref>I assign the date from Swinburne’s reading John Addington Symonds’ review of <title>Recollections</title>, in <title>The Academy</title>, October 28, 1882, while in Bradford-on-Avon (<title>Letters</title>, IV, 310, 311) and then presumably reading the book itself upon his return to The Pines.
                              </note>
                              <note xml:id="note_53" rendition="#block #small">
                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_53">3</ref>Nos. 43, 44 (August 2, 9, 1820), pp. [337]-344, [345]-352.</note>
                              <note xml:id="note_54" rendition="#block #small">
                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_54">4</ref>Swinburne quotes the phrase by Dante Gabriel Rossetti from a letter Caine quotes in <title>Recollections</title>, p. 179.</note>
                            </div>
                          </body>
                        </floatingText>
                      </item>  
                      <item>Letter 1241B pp. 349-350. To this letter might be added material in my collection relating to Swinburne's sisters and brother, The picture is of Isabel Swinburne and the memorial of her mentions the family piety.
                            <figure>
                                <graphic rend="margin-top:1em;padding:0;display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;" url="&imgpath;acs0000505-01-001.png"/>
                                <head rend="width:60%;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">Portrait of Isabel Swinburne.</head>
                                <figDesc>Portrait of Isabel Swinburne.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic rend="padding:0;display:block;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;" url="&imgpath;acs0000505-01-002.png"/>
                                <head rend="width:60%;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;">A memorial for Isabel Swinburne.</head>
                                <figDesc>A memorial for Isabel Swinburne.</figDesc>
                            </figure>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1247A. p. 354. Swinburne’s allusion to his “parabasis” of
                            Aristophanes’ “The Birds” should have a note: Published in <title>The
                                Athenaeum</title>, 30 October 1880, collected in <title>Studies in
                                Song</title> (1880).</item>
                      
                            <item>
                              <p>An added letter:</p>
                              
                              <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1301b">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                  <head rendition="#plainhead">1301B. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Lord Houghton</hi>
                                    <!-- <ref xml:id="ref_01" target="#note_01" rendition="#super">1</ref>-->
                                  </head>
                                  <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: Facsimile in an electronic “Occasional List,” September 13, 2013, Maggs Bros., Ltd.</hi></head>
                                  <div type="letter">
                                    <opener>
                                      <dateline><placeName rendition="#center #center-block">The Pines.<lb/>
                                        Putney Hill,<lb/>
                                        S.W.</placeName><date rendition="#right" when="1884-11-14">[November 14, 1884]<ref xml:id="ref_91" target="#note_91" rendition="#super">1</ref></date></dateline>
                                      <salute>Dear Lord Houghton</salute>
                                    </opener>
                                    <p>Very sorry to hear of your accident.  Watts &amp; I will come to luncheon on Sunday with pleasure.  He wrote yesterday to accept the invitation for Saturday, as we both thought that was the day named in your note.</p>
                                    <closer>
                                      <salute rendition="#ti-10">Ever yours truly,</salute>
                                      <signed rendition="#ti-12">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                    </closer>
                                  </div>
                                  <div type="notes">
                                    <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                    <note xml:id="note_91" rendition="#block  #small">
                                      <p><ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_91">1</ref>
                                        Swinburne notes that “just after” November 12, 1884, he had received “a pathetically pressing invitation to luncheon” with Houghton (<title>Letters</title>, V, 89).  Houghton had broken his collarbone—he fell out of bed when he dreamed Gladstone was pursuing him in a hansom cab.  In London, “closely confined to the house by the doctor’s orders, his old spirit reasserted itself, and he received with delight the friends who came to see him” (T. Wemyss Reid, <title>The Life, Letters, and Friendships of Richard Monckton Milnes, First Lord Houghton</title>, 2 vols. [London: Cassell &amp; Co., 1890], II, 430).</p>  
                                      <p>I am grateful to Polly Beauwin at Maggs Brothers for allowing me to print this letter from a facsimile in their “Occasional List.”  When I bought the letter for my collection, it was mailed, but never arrived.</p>
                                      <p>Someone has penciled on the letter “22 Feb. 1878,” a date presumably taken from the postmark on an accompanying envelope in the lot, bordered in black, according to the Maggs description, and surely addressed to Lord Houghton.   But that date for this letter is impossible as The Pines stationery makes clear—the envelope must have contained Swinburne’s letter to Lord Houghton, February 22 [1878] (<title>Letters</title>, IV, 45-46).</p><!-- note body -->
                                    </note>
                                  </div>
                                </body>
                              </floatingText>
                            </item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1322c">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                <head rendition="#plainhead">1322C.5. <hi rendition="#sc">To A. C. Swinburne,
                                    from Mary Louisa Molesworth</hi><ref xml:id="ref_08"
                                        rendition="#super" target="#note_08">1</ref></head>
                                <head rendition="#plainhead">
                                    <hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., The Harry Ransom Humanities Research
                                        Center, The University of Texas at Austin; printed in Terry L.
                                        Meyers, “Swinburne Shapes His Grand Passion: A Version by
                                        ‘Ashford Owen.’” <title>Victorian Poetry</title> 31:1 (Spring
                                        1993), 113-117. Included here with permission.</hi>
                                </head><div><opener>
                                            <address><addrLine rendition="#ti-9">85,  Lexham Gardens</addrLine><addrLine rendition="#ti-10">                        Kensington, W.</addrLine></address>
                                            <dateline rendition="#ti-10">
                                                <date> May 2nd [1885]</date>
                                            </dateline>
                                            <salute>My dear M<hi rendition="#super">r</hi>.
                                            Swinburne</salute>
                                        </opener><p rendition="#indent">I <hi rendition="#i">was</hi> in time for Miss Ogle<ref rendition="#super" target="#note_09" xml:id="ref_09">2</ref>—so <hi rendition="#i">my</hi> stupid mistake (not
                                            Yours) did no harm—Rather good! For I found Miss Ogle
                                            so “<hi rendition="#i">very, <hi rendition="#u">very</hi>, <hi rendition="#uu">very</hi></hi> anxious,” to see you,
                                            (she told me how to write the very’s) that <hi rendition="#i">she</hi> is staying a day later in town <hi rendition="#i">on purpose</hi>— Will you therefore come
                                            to luncheon on Tuesday—26<hi rendition="#super">th</hi>.—at
                                            1.30? This is the day I have arranged with Miss Ogle—
                                            Please let me have one word by return to say you <hi rendition="#i">will</hi> come—<ref rendition="#super" xml:id="ref_10" target="#note_10">3</ref> You
                                            don’t know how glad I shall be to have been the means of
                                            procuring an hour or two’s talk together for you
                                            &amp; your old friend—so you <hi rendition="#i">will</hi>
                                            come, won’t you? &amp; my blundering will have been
                                            lucky— Miss Ogle told me to tell you she remembers <hi rendition="#i">everything</hi>—all the readings &amp;
                                            consultations—she is working at her second novel <hi rendition="#i">now</hi>—&amp; retaining your names— </p><closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-10">Yours most truly</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-10">Louisa Molesworth</signed>
                                            <seg> &amp; “Mark”—the villain I think is
                                            one—</seg>
                                            </closer></div><div type="notes"><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/><note xml:id="note_08" rendition="#block #small">
                                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_08">1</ref> (1839-1921), the novelist and writer
                                                of children’s books.
                                            </note><note xml:id="note_09" rendition="#block #small">
                                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_09">2</ref> Anne Charlotte Ogle (1832-1918), a
                                                family friend from Northumberland and the writer (as
                                                Ashford Owen) of a novel, <title>The Story of
                                                  Catherine</title> (London: Macmillan and
                                                Company, 1885), on which, as this letter suggests,
                                                Swinburne collaborated. The plot incorporates in
                                                recognizable ways elements of Swinburne’s grand
                                                passions, including his relationship with Adah
                                                Isaacs Menken. Full details in the <title>Victorian
                                                  Poetry</title> article where the letter first
                                                appeared.
                                            </note><note xml:id="note_10" rendition="#block #small">
                                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_10">3</ref> Swinburne tried, but was, in the end,
                                                unable to attend the luncheon
                                                (<title>Letters</title>, V, 111-112).
                                        </note></div></body></floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1407B. p. 423. In line 9, difficulty were about <hi
                                rendition="#u">should be</hi> difficulty were absent</item>
                        <item>Letter 1407D. p. 424. In the date, [1887] <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> [1887?] </item>
                        <item>Letter 1461A. p. 441. In line 1, “Mackail” deserves a note: J. W.
                            Mackail (1859-1945), classicist and editor, the biographer of William
                            Morris.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1466B. p. 445. 
                            <p>In note 2, <title>Daily Mail</title> <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> <title>Daily News</title></p>
                            <p>The <title>Daily News</title> printed a public reply to Swinburne’s letters mentioned in this note: “Mr. Swinburne and the <title>Daily News</title>,” 29 March 1888.</p>
                        </item>
                        
                            
                        <item>Letter 1480. p. 449. In line 18, authorize the publication <hi
                                rendition="#u">should be</hi> authorise the publication</item>
                        <item>Letter 1508D. p. 475. In note 1, a direct and more likely source for
                        the quotations is Browning’s “Confessions,” ll. 35-36.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1526B. p. 485. To this letter might be added a footnote, an unrelated account of the conversation (including an amusing French name, Browning, Tennyson, Shakespeare, Fletcher, Hugo) during a luncheon at the Pines with Wilson Barrett (1846-1904), manager, playwright, and, at that moment, perhaps the most famous actor in England, accompanied by, most likely, Richard Le Gallienne (1866-1947), the poet and essayist who was at the time Barrett’s literary secretary.  Swinburne is described (“about middle height, has auburn hair and blue eyes”) as is his speaking:  “when he talked earnestly his eyes seemed filled with music.”  As for his reading, it “has a very great charm, a weird chanting quality.”  And in reading lines that may have especially affected him, “How sad that nought can win dear love / But loss of dear love—,” “he seemed then to forget all in the world but the poetry; his hand grew firm; his young face came out like the sun; his smile gathered to a great beam; and his eyes yearned away from the book with an ineffable tenderness”   (“Mr. Swinburne at Home,” <title>The Pall Mall Gazette</title>, 20 November 1889).
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="mi3">
                    <index indexName="nav"/>
                    <head rendition="#center #styled">Vol. III.—The More Important</head>
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>Letter 1540B. p. 12. In note 1, Trafalger <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> Trafalgar</item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1543a.5">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1543A.5. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Marion Harry Spielmann,<ref xml:id="ref_11" rendition="#super" target="#note_11">1</ref> from Walter Theodore Watts-Dunton</hi></head>
                                <head rendition="#plainhead #sc">Text: MS., Terry L. Meyers.</head><div type="letter"><opener>
                                            <address rendition="#center"><addrLine>Northcourt,</addrLine><addrLine>Newport,</addrLine><addrLine>Isle of Wight.</addrLine></address>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right">
                                                <date>22 Aug ! / 90</date>
                                            </dateline>
                                            <salute>My dear Mr Spielmann</salute>
                                        </opener><p rendition="#indent">I am staying here with Swinburne at &lt;his&gt; the
                                            house of his <add place="above">Aunt</add> Lady Mary
                                            Gordon; but as soon as I get back next week I will
                                            suggest an appointment with you. My article in the rough
                                            will be then written &amp; we will compare notes. I
                                            shall be seeing Lord Tennyson (who is at Aldworth) soon</p><closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-10">Yours ever</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-10">Theodore Watts</signed>
                                            <seg type="postscript" rendition="#block">P. S. Swinburne
                                                sends you kind remembrances</seg>
                                            </closer></div><div type="notes"><milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/><note xml:id="note_11" rendition="#block #small">
                                            <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_11">1</ref>Marion Harry Spielmann (1858-1948), critic, connoisseur, and
                                                editor of <title>The Magazine of Art</title>. No
                                                article by Watts-Dunton in <title>The Magazine of
                                                  Art</title> is listed in Tom J. Truss, jr.,
                                                “Theodore Watts-Dunton: A Primary Bibliography,”
                                                  <title>Bulletin of Bibliography</title>,
                                                23:5(May-August 1961), 114-117. This letter confirms
                                                the year of letter 1543C to be 1890.
                                        </note></div></body></floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1543C. p. 13. To note 2 should be added:
                                <p>The
                                soap referred to was no doubt Swinburne’s favorite, “Samphire Soap,”
                                “which was extensively advertised by a quotation from ‘King Lear’”:
                                “A. C. S. believed implicitly that it was highly charged with the
                                active principle of ozone. He sensed the wave in its odour, and the
                                suds in his bath were refreshing to him as the foam of the ocean”
                                (Clara Watts-Dunton, <title>The Home Life of Swinburne</title>
                                    [London: A. M. Philpot, 1922], p. 106). William Black wrote in 1888 that “a great poet of our own day, who is passionately fond of the sea, and is also an excellent swimmer, declares that, if you are pent up in town or country, you have only to use samphire soap in order to induce the impression that you have just come in from breasting the breakers off the rocks of Alderney or Sark” (“A Day's Stalking,” <title>Longman's Magazine</title>, <date when="1888-12-13">13 [December 1888]</date>, p. 179).</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1552B. p. 21. In note 3, add: The review was reprinted in
                                <title>Contemporaries of Shakespeare</title>, ed. Edmund Gosse and
                            Thomas James Wise (London: William Heinemann, 1919); see Bonchurch, XII,
                            307-320.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1556A.  p. 33. To the mention of William Bell Scott in note 2 should be added that in a letter of 29 November 1892, the Scottish writer William Sharp (1855-1905) took note of Swinburne’s anger at Scott’s <title>Autobiographical Notes</title> (1892): “Swinburne is going to slate it unmercifully (and very foolishly) in the December Fortnightly [“The New Terror,” 1 December 1892].  I was dining at his house in Putney the other day:  he was very excited over ‘The Monster’ to whom he has paid so many affectionate tributes in verse!” (See The William Sharp Archive. Ed. William F. Halloran. 1 June 2006 [<ptr target="http://www.sas.ac.uk/ies/cmps/Projects/Sharp/index.htm"/>]).  In a note to Sharp’s letter of 5 December 1892 to Watts-Dunton, Halloran suggests that Watts-Dunton had sent Sharp Swinburne’s manuscript or proofs for Sharp to use in writing his review of <title>Autobiographical Notes</title> (The Academy, 3 December 1892).  I sketch the relations between Sharp and Swinburne in my <title>The Sexual Tensions of William Sharp</title> (New York: Peter Lang, 1996), pp. 59-62. Included there is Sharp's poem, <title level="a">To Mr. A. C. Swinburne.</title>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1556C. p. 23. The manuscript of this letter is now in the collection of Terry L. Meyers.</item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1563a">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1563A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Edwin Arnold</hi><ref target="#note_fe29" rendition="#super">1</ref></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead #sc">Text: MS., Terry L. Meyers.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <address rendition="#block" rend="margin-left:22em;">
                        <addrLine>The Pines</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Putney Hill</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>SW</addrLine>
                    </address>
                                            <dateline rendition="#block" rend="margin-left:22em;margin-top:1em;"><date when="1891-07-08">July 8. 91</date></dateline>
                                            <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">I have begun a short essay on English poetry of the lighter kind (suggested by the appearance of Mr. Locker-Lampson’s ‘Lyra Elegantiarum’ in an enlarged edition.  I do not know when it will be ready for print, but if you should wish to have it for the Forum it is at your service when completed.</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rend="margin-left:16em;">Yours sincerely</salute>
                                            <signed rend="margin-left:18em;">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                            <address><addrLine>E. Arnold Esq.</addrLine></address>
                                        </closer>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_fe29"><ref rendition="#super">1</ref>
                                            (1832-1904), the poet and journalist, editor of <title>The Forum</title>, where Swinburne’s essay, <title level="a">Social Verse,</title> appeared (October 1891, collected in <title>SPP</title> [1894]).  
                                        </note>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1566a">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1566A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Francis Warre Cornish</hi><ref target="#note_fe21" rendition="#super">1</ref></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., Terry L. Meyers</hi>.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">I quite agree to your proposal &amp; fully approve of what has been done with regard to my ode.  I need not say it was not written with any afterthought of profit but simply as an offering of loyalty.</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rend="margin-left:6em;">In great haste</salute>
                                            <salute rend="margin-left:8em;">Yours very truly</salute>
                                            <signed rend="margin-left:10em;">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                            <dateline><date when="1891-07-30">July 30 [1891]</date></dateline>
                                        </closer>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_fe21"><ref rendition="#super">1</ref> I deduce the recipient and year from Swinburne’s family pressures at <date when="1891-07">the end of July 1891</date> and the likelihood that the letter concerns “Eton: An Ode.”  I guess too that Swinburne here is acquiescing to a further appearance of the poem, likely as set to the music (London and New York: Novello, Ewer and Co: [1891]) by Hubert Parry (<date from="1848" to="1918">1848-1918</date>, also an old Etonian).  The setting was anticipated in <title>The Athenaeum</title>, <date when="1891-05-30">30 May 1891</date>, where the poem was printed (p. 700).
                                        </note>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1575A. p. 27. In line 3, honor <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> honour</item>
                        <item>Letter 1599A. p. 39. To the note should be added that discussion of who should succeed Tennyson as Poet Laureate took place
                            even in the columns of the <title>New York Times</title>; see, for
                            example, Edmund Clarence Stedman’s endorsement of Swinburne in the issue
                            of 27 October 1895, p. 29: “with respect, then, to the morals of his
                            muse, … he has not written an ignoble line.”
                            <p>
                                In his <title>Private Diaries</title> (ed. Horace G. Hutchinson [New York: E. P. Dutton, 1922]), the well-connected civil servant Sir Algernon Edward West (1832-1921), private secretary to Gladstone from 1892, recorded some discussions of the Laureateship in his circle, even before Tennyson died.  He recorded in July 1891, for example, that Balfour favored Swinburne as Tennyson's successor (p. 19), but that George Murray, then Gladstone’s private secretary, looked into Swinburne's suitability only to discover his never having repudiated <title>Poems and Ballads</title> (1866),  his <title>Notes on Poems and  Reviews</title> (1866)], and his 1867 “[‘Appeal to England’] against the execution of the Manchester Fenians; so I am afraid that his chances of the Laureateship are over.”  Nevertheless, says West, “Swinburne, had he been possible, appeared to be the favorite, from the Prince of Wales downwards” (pp. 63, 64).  Indeed, he says outright that “the Prince of Wales was in favour of Swinburne” (p. 65) and quotes a letter from the Prince, 27 October 1892, to that effect (p. 69).
                            </p>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1599A.  p. 39. To the mention in note 1 of Swinburne’s likely being offered the Laureateship after the death of Tennyson should be added this further story, by “E. B. I-M,” who in the <title>Daily Telegraph</title> (12 April 12 1909, p. 10c) recalled being a passenger on the same voyage as William Morris to and from Norway in July and August 1896:
                            <quote rendition="#blockquote #nq">
                            I was a fellow-traveler with William Morris on his last sea voyage, taken in the unhappily fruitless search for health in 1896.  In the course of one of many delightful talks I had with him, he told me that Swinburne had been ‘sounded’ as to the acceptance of the Poet Laureateship, vacant by the death of Tennyson, and that Swinburne, though highly appreciating the implied honour, had declined because it was not consonant with ‘the fitness of things’ that the writer of regicide sonnets should be the official poet of a Court.   Morris added that after Swinburne’s refusal he himself was also ‘sounded,’ and that he too felt bound to decline, because, as he said, ‘people choose to regard me, and to call me, a Socialist.’</quote>
                            Jeremy Mitchell tells me that  “E.B.I-M” must surely have been Ernest Bruce Iwan-Muller (1853-1910), a journalist whose appointments included <title>Editor Manchester Courier</title> (1884-93), Assistant Editor <title>Pall Mall Gazette</title> (1893-96), and leader writer <title>Daily Telegraph</title> (1896-1910).     
                        </item>
                            
                        <item>Letter 1606B. p. 42. Dead Dr. Hake <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            Dear Dr. Hake</item>
                        <item>Letter 1612B. p. 44. In line 3, honor <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> honour</item>
                        <item>
                          Letter 1613A.  p. 45. I overlooked Cecil Lang’s use of this number; my letter 1613A should be numbered 1613C.
                          <p>To Lang’s note to his letter 1613A, on the publication of “Music: An Ode,” might be added that the poem also appeared in <title>The Times</title>, December 23, 1892, p. 6d.</p>
                          
                        </item>
                      <item>Letter 1619A.  p. 47. Jeremy Mitchell suggests that the chaffing letters exchanged by Swinburne and Mary Gordon Leith as if between schoolboys may have originated many years before, and cites a comment by Leith in <title>The Boyhood of Algernon Charles Swinburne</title>  (p. 21): “I think it was the following autumn [i.e., in 1864] which he [Swinburne] spent in Cornwall. My parents and I were in Scotland and I received constant letters from him. Among a great deal that is comic and clever, but only intelligible to one who understands our jokes and ‘characters’ under which we delighted to write, are some charming and graphic descriptions.”
                        
                      </item>
                        <item>Letter 1619C. p. 51. In note 1, <hi rendition="#i">Flight</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#i">Fight</hi></item>
                        <item>Letter 1649B. p. 73. In note 3, of lord <hi rendition="#u">should
                        be</hi> of lords</item>
                        <item>Letter 1654A. p. 79.  In note 1, the inscribed book was not <title>AOP</title> but <title>SPP</title>(1884); on the half-title Swinburne wrote, <q>Mary A. B. Gordon from her affectionate nephew AC Swinburne Nov. 8th 1894.</q>  A photograph of the inscription appears in <title>Miscellany 2006: Catalogue No. 123</title> (2006), issued by Ian Hodgkins &amp; Co. Ltd., item 79.</item>
                        <item>An added letter: 
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1694b">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1694B. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Walter Theodore Watts-Dunton</hi></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: An Unidentified Auction Clipping, Terry L. Meyers</hi>.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right">Barking Hall</dateline>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right"><date when="1896-08-07">August 7, '96</date></dateline>
                                            <salute>My Dear Walter,</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">I have read your note, &amp; the letter<ref xml:id="ref_25" rendition="#super" target="#note_25">1</ref> which I return herewith, to my mother.  She will not hear of her name being published, whether in the title or sub-title (I mean in a note to the text) of the poem, but does not so positively object to a note explaining that the verses were written for the birthday of the author’s mother.  I must say I should have thought that the very densest of human skulls could not have misconstrued the opening words—‘Fourscore years &amp; seven’—or failed to connect them with the closing phrase—‘She who here first drew the breath of life she gave me.’</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-15">Ever affly yours,</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-15">A. C. Swinburne</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_25" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_25" rendition="#super">1</ref>For the note, see <title>Uncollected Letters</title>, III, 108, where the letter is identified as being from James Knowles, editor of <title>The Nineteenth Century</title>, where Swinburne’s “The High Oaks, Barking Hall, July 19th, 1896” was to appear in September.
                                        </note>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item> 
                        <item>Letter 1695A. p. 109. In l. 3, adapted <hi rendition="#u">should
                        be</hi> adopted</item>
                        <item>Letter 1713A. pp. 115-116. To note 1 might be added this: Cockerell later recalled a visit to The Pines at about this time during which he urged Swinburne to send to the museum at San Gimignano his “poem on San Gimignano” (the context [see <title>The Times</title>, 8 August 1938, p. 13g] alludes to an account of a visit Swinburne in 1903 [See <title>Uncollected Letters</title>, 1773C, on which, see below], but does not identify the poem with certainty; I suspect it may be “Relics” [<title>PB<hi rendition="#n">II</hi></title> (1878)]):  “He readily consented and I sent his transcript, with his accompanying letter, to the museum.  They were duly acknowledged, and I learnt from a subsequent visitor that both documents were placed on exhibition” (“Swinburne and San Gimignano,” <title>The Times</title>, 17 August 1938, p. 11f).
                            
                            
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1717A. p. 116. This letter has been printed in José María
                            Martínez Domingo, “Una Carta Inédita de Rubén Darío a Algernon Charles
                            Swinburne.” <title>Bulletin of Hispanic Studies</title> [Glasgow
                            University], 74:3, 279-92.</item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1734bis">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1734 <hi rendition="#sc">bis. To: Richard Dacre Archer-Hind </hi><ref target="#note_fe22" rendition="#super">1</ref></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., Terry L. Meyers.</hi>.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <address rend="margin-left:18em;">
                        <addrLine>The Pines</addrLine>
                    </address>
                                            <dateline rend="margin-top:1em;margin-left:20em;"><date when="1898-08-04">Aug. 4. 98</date></dateline>
                                            <salute>My dear Sir</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">It can hardly be necessary for me to say how welcome you are to print any of my verses to which your contributors have done the honour of translating them.  It would greatly interest me to read the version of ‘The Garden of Prosperpine’ in Greek elegiacs.
                                        </p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rend="margin-left:12em;">Yours sincerely</salute>
                                            <signed rend="margin-left:14em;">A.C. Swinburne</signed>
                                            <address>
                    <addrLine>R. D. Archer-Hind Esq</addrLine>
                </address>
                                        </closer>
                                        
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_fe22" rendition="#block #small"><ref rendition="#super">1</ref> See <title>Uncollected Letters</title>, III, 133 and note for the full context of this letter and the added letter below,  1735 bis.
                                        </note>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>An added letter:
                            
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1735bis">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1735 <hi rendition="#sc">bis. To: Richard Dacre Archer-Hind </hi><ref target="#note_fe23" rendition="#super">1</ref></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., Terry L. Meyers.</hi>.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <address rend="margin-left:18em;">
                        <addrLine>The Pines</addrLine>
                        <addrLine>Putney Hill</addrLine>
                        <addrLine rend="margin-left:4em;">S.W.</addrLine>
                    </address>
                                            <dateline rend="margin-top:1em;margin-left:20em;"><date when="1898-09-11">Sept. 11. 98</date></dateline>
                                            <salute>Dear Sir</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">I am heartily ashamed to be so late in thanking you for your great kindness in sending me a transcript of the exquisitely  beautiful version you have done me the honour &lt;of&gt; to make of my ‘Garden of Proserpine’.  I waited to do so till I had made a thorough study of it: &amp; between the oppressive &amp; enervating heat of these last weeks<ref rendition="#super" target="#note_fe24">2</ref>  (more trying to me than any other sort of weather) &amp; a number of other calls on my time &amp; energies, it is, I am shocked to find, just over a month since I ought to have acknowledged the kindness shown me &amp; the honour done me.  Your Greek seems to me quite as musical—whatever you say to the contrary—as my English <add place="above">&#x2041;can possibly be considered</add>: &amp; the wonderful &amp; subtle felicity of rendering repeatedly struck me with astonishment as well as delight.  I wish I were scholar enough to make my praise &amp; admiration on that score worth having: but I am not, I hope, quite incapable of appreciation as well as &lt;of&gt; gratitude.
                                        </p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rend="margin-left:12em;">Yours very truly</salute>
                                            <signed rend="margin-left:14em;">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                        
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_fe23" rendition="#block #small"><ref rendition="#super">1</ref> See <title>Uncollected Letters</title>, III, 133 and note for the full context of this letter and the added letter above, 1734 bis.
                                        </note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_fe24" rendition="#block #small"><ref rendition="#super">2</ref>   See “The Hot Weather,” <title>The Times</title>, 9 September 1898, p. 10b-c.  Temperatures had been above 90 F.</note>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>An added letter: 
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1738a">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1738A. <hi rendition="#sc">To: ?</hi></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS., Terry L. Meyers</hi>.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <dateline>
                                                <address>
                                                    <addrLine rendition="#ti-18">The Pines,</addrLine>
                                                    <addrLine rendition="#ti-20">Putney Hill,</addrLine>
                                                </address>
                                            </dateline>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right"><date when="1898-12-29">Dec. 29. 98</date></dateline>
                                            <salute>Dear Madam</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">You are most welcome to the use of my poems about children—any and as many as you please.</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-15">Yours very truly</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-17">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                      <item>
                        <p>An added letter:</p>
                        <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1713b">
                          <index indexName="nav"/>
                          <body>
                            <head rendition="#plainhead">1739B. <hi rendition="#sc">To: William Clark Russell</hi><ref xml:id="ref_71" target="#note_71" rendition="#super">1</ref>
                              <!-- <ref xml:id="ref_01" target="#note_01" rendition="#super">1</ref>-->
                            </head>
                            <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text:
                              Printed in <title>The Morning Post</title>, January 20, 1899,  p. 7.</hi></head>
                            <div type="letter">
                              <opener>
                                <dateline rendition="#right">
                                  <placeName>The Pines, Putney-hill, S.W.</placeName> <date when="1899-01-17">Jan. 17. [1899]</date></dateline>
                              </opener>
                              <p>Dear Sir, — Your name is more than sufficient introduction to any Englishman and lover of the sea. I among many thousands such, have to thank you for hours of delight. I can only at present assure you of my cordial sympathy with your noble and patriotic enterprise on behalf of Mercantile Jack.<ref xml:id="ref_72" target="#note_72" rendition="#super">2</ref>  The son of a sailor who served under Collingwood need add no further assurance of his sincerity. —</p>  
                              <closer>
                                <salute>Yours very gratefully,</salute>
                                <signed rendition="#ti-10">A. C. Swinburne</signed>
                              </closer>
                            </div>
                            <div type="notes">
                              <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                              <note xml:id="note_71" rendition="#block  #small">
                                <p><ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_71">1</ref>(1844-1911), author of nautical novels and columnist for <title>The Daily Telegraph</title> where he pushed for better conditions for merchant seamen.</p>
                                <p>A note by Cecil Lang to Swinburne’s letter of February 7, 1899 (<title>Letters</title>, VI, 135) and the letters immediately following suggest the broad context of this letter in the midst of a controversy generated by a letter in the <title>Morning Post</title>, December 12, 1898, from William Clark Russell about “various evils in the merchant navy.”</p>  
                                <p>Swinburne’s letter is printed with an accompanying letter from Russell, January 19, 1899: “I am in receipt of the enclosed letter from that master-spirit of this age and poet of all time—Algernon Charles Swinburne.  His reference to myself embarrasses me in my desire to make his noble voice heard, but I feel it is due to the cause of Mercantile Jack that our well-beloved poet’s message should be delivered.”</p>
                                <p>In an obituary for Russell likely picked up from a periodical in England, Swinburne is quoted as saying that Russell “is the greatest master of the sea, living or dead, and his name is a household word wherever the English language is spoken and the splendid qualities of the British sailor known and understood.” “Master of the Sea. Death of Mr. Clark Russell,” <title>Timaru Herald</title> (New Zealand), December 27, 1911, p. 5.</p>
                                
                                <!-- note body -->
                              </note>
                              <note xml:id="note_72" rendition="#block  #small">
                                <ref rendition="#super" target="#ref_72">2</ref>The generic term for a merchant sailor (see Dickens’ “Poor Mercantile Jack” in <title>The Uncommerical Traveller</title>).
                              </note>
                            </div>
                          </body>
                        </floatingText>
                      </item>
                        
                        <item>Letter 1743B. p. 151. In line 7, spins? <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> spins?’</item>
                        <item>Letter 1769A. p. 193. In the signature, C. <hi rendition="#u">should
                        be</hi> A.C.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1773C. pp. 198-200. 
                            <p>
                            My guess in note 9 as to the author of this account of a visit with Swinburne was wrong.  “M.B.” is Mario Borsa (1870-1951), Italian critic and journalist, who was living in London at the time (see <title>Letters</title>, VI, 166).  Borsa visited The Pines 20 March 1903, not 1902, as he misremembered; given this corrected date, 1773C should be located later in the volume. </p>
                            <p>
                            Borsa’s account in 1773C is a redacted version of one he printed in <title>The English Stage of Today</title>, trans. Selwyn Brinton (London: John Lane, 1908).  Some of the material elided may have an interest, as, for example, his descriptions of:
                                <list rend="list-style-type: lower-alpha; margin-left: 4em; margin-top: 1em; margin-bottom: 1em;">
                                <item>
                            Swinburne’s study: “His study looks out upon a garden, embellished by a statuette from the hand of Dante Gabriel Rossetti.  The walls of the drawing-room, study, and dining-room are covered with memorials of the glorious pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood — pictures, portraits, designs, and sketches, by Burne-Jones, Rossetti, Morris, and Madox Brown.  In his study there are also reproductions of some of Turner's Italian landscapes” (p. 203).
                                </item>
                                <item>
                            Swinburne himself: “While he was again expressing to me his satisfaction at the remarks of the Minister Galimberti [see <title>Letters</title>, VI, 166 and Leith, pp. 97-98], and the pleasure he had experienced at finding himself still remembered in Italy, I contemplated him. Swinburne — whose lineaments are reproduced to perfection in the celebrated portrait by Watts — is short, slender, and fragile in appearance, with narrow, sloping shoulders. His physical frame is a <foreign xml:lang="fr" rendition="#i">quantité negligéable</foreign>; the man's entire personality is concentrated in his head. A fine forehead, both wide and lofty, on either side of which falls a tuft of wavy, whitish hair tinged with red, an aquiline nose, a prominent chin beneath a sunken mouth, a scanty beard, white at the roots and reddish at the tip, and two large glowing, shining blue eyes — eyes full of youthful vitality.  And he was even then sixty-three years of age!  Who would have guessed it!  Certainly no one from those eyes, any more than from his copious flow of living, palpitating speech” (pp. 203-204).
                                </item>
                                <item>
                            Swinburne on listening to Mazzini: “‘I shall never forget the hours I passed with him. On these occasions I rarely spoke; I listened reverently to him. After having known Mazzini, I began to understand Christ and His Gospel’” (p. 204).
                                </item>
                                <item>
                            a book by Mazzini dedicated to Swinburne: “‘Do you know, he had it bound for me himself!’  And he drew my attention to the beauty of the binding. He told me that he remained in correspondence with Mazzini and with Signora Venturi up to the last” (p. 205).
                                </item>
                                <item>
                            Don Luigi Pecori’s being delighted at the English reception of Garibaldi: “‘When I related this to Mazzini, he immediately made a note of the canon's name in his pocket-book’”  (p. 206).</item>
                                <item>
                            an auction at Brescia: “‘And I had no money! Stuff for which the National Gallery would have paid millions! (Wouldn't they, Theodore?’ —‘Yes, yes!’ said Mr. Watts-Dunton. ‘Now tell him about Florence.’)” (p. 206).</item>
                                <item>
                            Landor:  “‘Look here !’ (He fetched a volume of Landor's works, and showed me the portrait on the first page). ‘Well?’ ‘A typical John Bull!’ was my remark. ‘Quite true! But I wish,’ added Swinburne, ‘that John Bull, like Landor, were a champion of every truly noble cause !’” (p. 206).</item>
                                <item>
                            the books Swinburne displayed: “With the admiration of all true pre-Raphaelites for ‘craftsmanship,’ he drew my attention to the elegance, solidity, and good taste of the bindings. He showed me a Boccaccio, two fine editions of the <title>Negromante</title> and the <title>Suppositi</title> of Ariosto, and a Bembo picked up for a few pence at Bristol” (p. 207); and, a bit further on, “‘Oh, do you know that book of Giambattista della Porta on the ‘Physiognomy of Man?’  (And taking it up he began to turn over its pages, showing me the illustrations.) ‘As you know, Della Porta claimed to have established, from certain physiological affinities, corresponding moral affinities between man and the lower animals.  Rossetti believed in it. I think that is so funny!  Look at this portrait of Pico della Mirandola.  What an extraordinary expression!  And the face of Cæsar Borgia here — the face of a born leader of men.’   At this point Mr. Watts-Dunton interrupted him with a smile to tell me that Swinburne was writing a tragedy on the subject of Cæsar Borgia” (pp. 207-208).</item>
                                <item>
                            Swinburne’s work on Cæsar Borgia: “He continued to talk to me while searching for the manuscript, and I gathered from his remarks that Swinburne had devoted much detailed historical research to this subject” (p. 208).</item>
                                <item>
                            Swinburne’s last words to Borsa on having spent two hours talking about “‘dear old Italy’”: “‘Thanks, thanks!’” (p. 209).
                                </item>
                            </list>
                            </p>
                          <!-- jawalsh: added material from new addition 2012-11-03 --><p>To Mario Borsa’s account of the disorderly library within The Pines might be added a further glimpse in the application by Thomas St. Edmund Hake (1845-1917) for a Civil List Pension from the Royal Literary Fund:
                          <cit rendition="#blockquote">
                            <quote>
<p><hi rendition="#uc">The petition</hi> of the undersigned humbly sheweth: —</p> 
                              <p rendition="#indent">That your Petitioners humbly submit for your gracious consideration the case of <persName rendition="#uc">Thomas St. Edmund Hake</persName>, who resides at 38 Amerland Road, West Hill, Wandsworth, in the County of London, with the object of soliciting for him a place on the Civil list.</p>
                              <p rendition="#indent">That Thomas St. Edmund Hake is 71 years of age and is married, with a delicate wife and three children, aged respectively 21, 17, and 13 (the eldest child being a daughter who, owing to her mother’s ill-health, manages the housekeeping) entirely dependent upon him. </p>
                              <p rendition="#indent">That he is the eldest son of the late Dr. Gordon Hake, who was a first cousin of General Gordon and a famous Author and Poet.</p> 
<ab type="milestone">……………………………………………………………………</ab>
                              <p rendition="#indent">That for the last eleven years of Algernon Charles Swinburne’s life, and for the last fourteen years of Theodore Watts Dunton’s life, he acted as their Secretary, and that for 38 years he was their most intimate friend. During his Secretaryship a pension of £250 was offered to Mr. Swinburne but courteously declined.</p>
                              <p rendition="#indent">That while acting as Secretary he devoted all his time and energy to the work before him from 8 a.m. to 8 p.m. every day, receiving at first £100 a year, which after eight years was increased to £150 a year. He was therefore compelled to relinquish his own literary pursuits and career, though he was described by Watts Dunton in the Athenæum, 1895, as ‘a rising novelist’. Mr. James Douglas wrote in the ‘Star’, November 19th. 1915 : — 
                              <cit rendition="#blockquote">
                                <quote>
                                  <p rendition="#indent">‘The World will never know what Mr. Hake sacrificed during his long and affectionate devotion to his old friend.  He was his slave, his willing slave.  He might have won for himself fame as a novelist if he had not ungrudgingly given his whole life to the drudgery of absolutely unselfish self-immolation.  Mr. Hake possessed the sweetest and gentlest and kindest of natures, and he never wearied. His capacity for toil was amazing.  There was a time when The Pines was choked to the roof with all sorts of literary lumber.  The only man who could find anything was Mr. Hake.  I remember a room which was so hopelessly congested that there was barely space for two chairs.  But Hake held every clue in his hands.  I hope Mr. Hake will give us a stout volume of reminiscences. Nobody could tell the story of The Pines as he can tell it. He alone could play the Boswell to Swinburne and his old friend.  What stories he could relate!  The danger is that he may put off the task too long.’</p>
                                </quote>
                              </cit>
                              </p>
                              <p rendition="#indent">That he has no private income, and that his only temporary means of support is a legacy of £200 left to him by the late of Theodore Watts Dunton.
                              </p>
                            </quote>
                            <bibl>(Hake, Thomas St Edmund. Thomas St Edmund Hake. 1845-1917. n.d. MS Archives of the Royal Literary Fund: Archives of the Royal Literary Fund 3019. World Microfilms. <title>Nineteenth Century Collections Online</title>. Web. 6 Feb. 2014. Document URL  <ptr target="http://tinyurl.galegroup.com/tinyurl/CwuC5"/>)</bibl>
                          </cit>
                          </p>
                          <p>And both of these glimpses might be supplemented by the account by Arthur Christopher Benson of his visit to The Pines, April 4, 1903 (p. 64): <ptr target="https://openlibrary.org/books/OL7238900M/Diary"/>.</p>
                          <p>Hake (with Arthur Compton-Rickett) did contribute to hagiographic accounts of those living at The Pines in <title>The Letters of Algernon Charles Swinburne, with Some Personal Recollections</title> (London: John Murray, 1918) and <title>The Life and Letters of Theodore Watts-Dunton</title>, 2 vols. (London: T. C. and E. C. Jack, 1916).</p>
                          
                        </item>
                      <item>Letter 1773E. p. 203. To the note on “First Fault for the Hundredth Time” should be added:  In “He’s Catching it! Isn’t it Nuts: Algernon Charles Swinburne’s Eton Swishing Play” (<title>TLS</title>, January 10, 2014, pp. 14-15), Peter Leggatt dates “First Fault for the Hundredth Time” to Swinburne’s days at Eton; that dating is the premise for an elaborate analysis of the work (see <ptr target="http://www.the-tls.co.uk/tls/public/article1360287.ece"/>).  
                        <p>But even without seeing the handwriting, I am confident “First Fault” is one of Swinburne’s later fantasies about schoolboy flagellation.  Its premise, a punishment for whispering in church, may have come to Swinburne as he wrote, January 14 [1879], his response to a poem by Mary Gordon Leith, “The Whistle in Church” (see <title>Uncollected Letters</title>, II, 162).  He mentions “First Fault” in a letter of June 7, 1906 in a way that suggests the work is one that she had possessed (see <title>Uncollected Letters</title>, II, 275).</p>
                        
                      </item>
                        <item>Letter 1774D. p. 211. To note 1, mentioning a June 1906 production of <title>Atalanta in Calydon</title>, might be added a review in <title>The Times</title>, “Performance of Mr. Swinburne’s ‘Atalanta in Calydon,’” 8 June 1906, p. 7f.  The review suggests some timidity in the redaction, avoiding the word “God,” for example, perhaps because the several performances mentioned at the Crystal Palace were “in aid of the Church of England Society for Waifs and Strays.”   One of the Society’s orphanages, for girls, was located in Wimbledon, not far from Putney.  A subsequent performance at the Scala Theatre was to benefit “the Bedford College for Women site and building scheme.”
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1774H. p. 217. This letter was drafted for the signers by Arthur Symons, according to Karl Beckson and John M. Munro, who include it in their edition of <title>Arthur Symons: Selected Letters</title> (Iowa City: University of Iowa Press, 1989), p. 166.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1807F. p. 246. In line 21, ‘Ginerva’ <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> ‘Ginevra’</item>
                        <item>Letter 1819A. p. 263. To note 1 should be added:
                            <p>A
                            largely unconvincing account of life at The Pines (<title>The Sunday
                                Times</title>, April 11, 1909; p. 7f) claims that the marriage of
                            Watts-Dunton “made no difference to the domestic companionship of the
                            two men” and that “it was her [Clara Watts-Dunton’s] habit to visit The
                            Pines every day to minister to the creature comforts of the poet and the
                            critic.”</p>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1827E. p. 276. In line 2, honor <hi rendition="#u">should
                        be</hi> honour</item>
                        <item>An added letter: 
                            
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1863d">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1863D. <hi rendition="#sc">To: Lucy Margaret Lamont</hi><ref xml:id="ref_26" target="#note_26" rendition="#super">1</ref></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: MS.,<ref xml:id="ref_27" target="#note_27" rendition="#super">2</ref> Terry L. Meyers</hi>.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <opener>
                                            <dateline>
                                                <address>
                                                    <addrLine rendition="#ti-18">The Pines,</addrLine>
                                                    <addrLine rendition="#ti-20">11, Putney Hill,</addrLine>
                                                    <addrLine rendition="#ti-22">S.W.</addrLine>
                                                </address>
                                            </dateline>
                                            <dateline rendition="#right"><date when="1909-03-29">March 29. 9</date></dateline>
                                            <salute>Dear Madam</salute>
                                        </opener>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">You are welcome to the use of my verses.  The publishers, to whom I usually leave all such matters, will raise no objections when I do not.</p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-15">Yours sincerely </salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-17">AC Swinburne</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_26" rendition="#block #small"><p><ref target="#ref_26" rendition="#super">1</ref>The widow of the artist T. R. Lamont.  In a letter of 28 March 1909 (now in the Brotherton Collection, Leeds University and quoted with permission), Mrs. Lamont asked to print in an anthology “The Pilgrims” and “Man’s Soul”  (from <title>Songs before Sunrise</title>, the latter being stanzas 15-18 of “The Prelude”) and the chorus “We have seen thee, O Love” (from <title>Atalanta in Calydon</title>).  The poems duly appeared in <title>A Coronal</title> (London: Martin Secker, 1911).  In her letter, Mrs. Lamont asked, “If you should graciously allow me to include these it will be necessary also to gain the sanction of your publishers, will it not?” and commented, “My name may bring a remembrance to you from long years ago, for my husband, T. R. Lamont, used to tell me of knowing you in the sixties.”</p>
                                            <p>Thomas Reynolds Lamont (1826-1899) is a shadow in E. R. and J. Pennell, <title>The Life of James McNeil Whistler</title> (Philadelphia: J. B. Lippincott, 1908), where he is met by Whistler in Paris at Charles Gabriel Gleyre's studio and where he simply strolls and jokes with Whistler.  He is still wispy in Stanley Weintraub's <title>Whistler: A Biography</title> (New York: Weybright and Talley, 1974), but he takes on more flesh in Leonée Ormond's <title>George Du Maurier</title> ([Pittsburg: University of Pittsburg Press, 1969).  And of course he lives, more or less forever, as "the Laird" in Du Maurier's <title>Trilby</title>.</p>
                                        </note>
                                        <note xml:id="note_27" rendition="#block #small"><ref target="#ref_27" rendition="#super">2</ref>The letter, one of the last two Swinburne is known to have written, is tipped into a first edition of <title>Atalanta in Calydon</title> (1865) inscribed by Swinburne (but not signed): “To Mary E. Ranken / July 9 1865.”  I do not know who Mary Ranken is; the only Ranken I can find even on the far periphery of Swinburne’s circle is R. B. Ranken, at Balliol in 1859 as a Snell Exhibitioner.
                                        </note>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1861B. p. 299. To this letter might be added a footnote, an unrelated account via Watts-Dunton of Christmas 1908 at The Pines—Swinburne’s reading Dickens, his never having been in better health, and his habitual walk of “two or three hours daily, and there is hardly a child he meets on his way that he does not stop to give pence to and talk to.”   Swinburne comments, according to Watts-Dunton, on the efforts by suffragettes in the preceding weeks to draw attention to their cause (e.g., their intrusion into the House of Commons and interruption of David Lloyd George at the Albert Hall): “‘they have recently shown that they are quite unfitted for the exercise of the vote.  Theoretically women should be entitled to vote.   We all are children of the same mother, Nature, and should be treated equally, but in practice I am afraid that the thing is wholly impossible’” (“Swinburne’s Christmas,” <title>The New York Times</title>, 27 December 1908, p. 2c).
                        </item> 
                        <item xml:id="letter1863g">Letter 1863G.  pp. 305-306.  A note to the lines by William Michael Rossetti should be added:
                            <p>Part of this passage appears in Roger W. Peattie, “Swinburne’s Funeral,” <title>Notes and Queries</title>, 21 (December 1974), 467.  Peattie identifies the document as a letter from Rossetti to William Holman Hunt.</p>
                            <p>To Peattie’s account of Swinburne’s funeral and to Rooksby’s photograph of the service (see below) and account by Helen Rossetti (Rooksby, <title>A. C. Swinburne</title>, pp. 284-286) might be added a series of photographs<!--<ref xml:id="ref_28" target="#note_28" rendition="#super">1</ref>--> published by contemporary periodicals as well as further information I've compiled. See my article <ref target="http://www.purl.org/swinburnearchive/xml/acs0000504-01/"><title level="a">Some Notes Relating to Swinburne's Funeral.</title></ref></p></item>
                               
                        <item>An added letter: 
                            <floatingText rendition="#textbox" xml:id="l1899">
                                <index indexName="nav"/>
                                <body>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead">1899.<hi rendition="#sc">To: ?</hi></head>
                                    <head rendition="#plainhead"><hi rendition="#sc">Text: <title>The Daily Telegraph</title>, 12 April 1909</hi>, p. 10c.</head>
                                    <div>
                                        <p rendition="#indent">I am not a professional or official poet, and could not undertake to write any verse—patriotic or other—to order.<ref xml:id="ref_29" target="#note_29" rendition="#super">1</ref></p>
                                        <closer>
                                            <salute rendition="#ti-15">Yours very truly,</salute>
                                            <signed rendition="#ti-15">A. C. Swinburne</signed>
                                        </closer>
                                        <postscript>
                                            <p rendition="#indent"/>
                                        </postscript>
                                    </div>
                                    <div type="notes">
                                        <milestone unit="section" rendition="#hr-50"/>
                                        <note xml:id="note_29" rendition="#block  #small"><ref target="#ref_29" rendition="#super">1</ref>The letter, which I cannot date, is introduced with the comment that it was “written in reply to a request that he [Swinburne] would write a poem on certain subjects.”</note>
                                    </div>
                                </body>
                            </floatingText>
                        </item>
                        
                        <item>p. [317]. l. 5 Rev.? <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> Rev</item>
                        <item>Letter 98. p. 326. Lytton-Bulwer <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            Bulwer-Lytton</item>
                        <item>Letter 291. p. 333. Tyrwitt <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            Tyrwhitt</item>
                        <item>Letter 1752. p. 366. A note should be added: The letter is reproduced
                            in facsimile in John S. Mayfield, “Swinburne and the Agnostic,”
                                <title>Swinburneiana : A Gallimaufry of Bits and Pieces about
                                Algernon Charles Swinburne</title> (Gaithersburg MD: The Waring
                            Press, 1974), p. 19. Mayfield’s note elaborates on the recipient and on
                            an earlier printing of the letter (p. 179).</item>
                        <item>In Appendix B, in addition, I should have called attention to Anna
                            Unsworth’s comment on Letter 1857 in <title>Letters</title> (28
                            September 1908): “Swinburne on Mrs Gaskell.” <title>Notes and
                                Queries</title>, 38 (236):3(September 1991), 323-24.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="indexappendixb">
            <index indexName="nav"/>
			<head rendition="#styled">An Index to Appendix B</head>
			<div type="navigation">
				<p rendition="#center">
					<ref type="simple" target="#a">A</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#b">B</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#c">C</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#d">D</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#e">E</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#f">F</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#g">G</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#h">H</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#I">I</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#j">J</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#k">K</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#l">L</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#m">M</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#n">N</ref> | O | <ref type="simple"
						target="#p">P</ref> | Q | <ref type="simple"
						target="#r">R</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#s">S</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#t">T</ref> | U | <ref type="simple"
						target="#v">V</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#w">W</ref> | X | Y | Z
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="index">
				<div xml:id="a">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Academy</title>. 350, 362, 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Angus, W. C. 352</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Arnold, E. 359</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Arnold, M. 331, 332, 350, 353, 354</item>
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Athenaeum</title>. 347</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="B">
					<list rendition=" #noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Benson. A. C. 366</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Black, W. 349, 360</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Blakeney, E. H. 366</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Blind, M. 336</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Boker, G. 337</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Boyd, A. 325</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Brown, A. W. 347</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Brown, J. 368</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Browning, R. 324</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Buisson, B. 351</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Bullen, A. H. 358, 368</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Bulwer-Lytton. 326</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Burne-Jones, E. 324, 334, 344, 354, 355</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Burton, R. 336, 347</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Butler, Josephine. 326</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="c">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Cambridge Union. 329</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Cannibal Club. 336</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Chapman, G. R. 327</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Chatto, A. 348, 349, 351, 352, 353, 357, 360</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Chivers, T. H. 358</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Cockerell, S. 364, 367</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Coleridge, E. H. 357, 365, 366</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Coleridge, S. T. 365, 368</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Collingwood, J. F. 331</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Collins, J. C. 346</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Colvin, S. 340</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Conway, M. D. 328</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Cook, E. T. 368</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Corelli, M. 355</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Cornish, F. W. 361</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Cornwall, B. 333</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Cotton, J. S. 362</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Craik, D. M. 351</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Crosbie, H. W. 323</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Crosskey, H. W. 323</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="d">
					<list rendition=" #noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Daily Graphic</title>. 361</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Dante. 332</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Davidson, J. 348</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Davidson, J. M. 357</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">de Sade. 338</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">de Saint Victor, P. 339</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Dowden, E. 358, 359</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Downes, R. P. 368</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Dryden-Mundy, P. 366</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="e">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Echo de Paris</title>. 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Examiner</title>. 341</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="f">
					<list rendition=" #noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Farrell, E. I. 366</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Fiedler, H. G. 366</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Forman, H. B. 339, 349, 351, 353, 354</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Friswell, J. H. 331</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="g">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Goethe. 368</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Gosse, E. 344, 346, 347, 350, 352, 354, 355, 356, 358, 362, 363, 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Graham, L. 330</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Graves, C. L. 360</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Grosart, A. B. 365</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="h">
					<list rendition=" #noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Halliwell-Phillipps, J. O. 349</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Hake, T. S.E. 367</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Harrison, E. 361</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Hatch, E. 323</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Haweis, H. R. 335</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Hayne, P. H. 346, 347, 348</item>
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Hedda Gabbler</title>. 363</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Herkless, M. K. 366</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Horne, R. H. 353</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Hotten, J. C. 328, 332, 340</item>
					    <item xml:id="id01" rendition="#hang">Houghton, Lord. 323, 324, 326, 349</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Howell, G. A. 331</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Hugo. V. 323, 330, 333, 334, 335, 339, 341, 342, 354, 356</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="I">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Ibsen. 363</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Inchbold, J. W. 359</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Ingram, J. H. 367</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="j">
					<list rendition=" #noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Jackson, W. 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Jameson, F. 326</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Jourde, F. 349</item>
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Journal des Débats</title>. 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Joyce, T. H. 361</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="k">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Kirkup, S. 324, 332</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Knight, J. 327, 338, 343, 344</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Knowles, J. 364</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="l">
					<list rendition=" #noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Landor. W. S. 346, 363</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Lee, S. 360</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Lippincott, F. 337</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Locker Lampson, F. 339</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Low, S. 360</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Lytton, Lord. 328</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="m">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">MacColl, N. 346, 347</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">MacLehose, J. 361</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Marston, P. B. 330, 338, 342, 351</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Mayfield, J. S. 339</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Mazzini, G. 346</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Milnes, R. See <ref type="simple"
								target="#id01">Lord Houghton.</ref></item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Minto, W. 362</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Morley, J. 333, 335, 336, 339, 340, 341, 342, 343, 344, 345, 350, 351,
							352, 353, 357</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Morris, W. 344, 354, 363, 364</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Motherwell. 336</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Moulton, L. C. 347</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Myers, F. W. H. 364</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="nn">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Nesbitt, E. 359</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Nichol, J. 323, 330, 342, 345, 346, 352, 356, 361, 362</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="p">
					<list rendition=" #noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Pall Mall Gazette</title>. 368</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Parnell, C. S. 360</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Parsons, J. R. 326</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Payne, J. B. 343</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Peacock, T. L. 351</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Périé, R. 343</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Poel, W. 362</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Powell, G. 330, 332, 339</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Proctor, Mrs. 332</item>
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Punch</title>. 358</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="r">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Redway, G. 357</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Reid, W. W. 361</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Rice, S. S. 344</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Rossetti, C. 357</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Rossetti, G. B. 367</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Rossetti, D. G. 334, 336, 337, 338, 339, 367</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Rossetti, W. M. 327, 329, 333, 336, 347, 349, 354, 355, 356, 357, 358,
							366, 367</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Royal Literary Fund, Council. 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Ruskin, J. 326, 328</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Rutherford, M. See <ref type="simple" target="#id02">W. H. White</ref></item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="s">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Saffi, A. 336</item>
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>St. James's Gazette</title>. 359, 360</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">St. John Tyrwhitt, R. 333</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Salaman, C. K. 368</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Scott, W. B. 325, 352, 362</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Shakespeare. 368</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Sheppard, R. H. 357</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Shelley, P. B. 333, 358, 340</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Shields, F. J. 356</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Shorter, C. K. 363, 366</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Solomon, S. 333, 334, 338</item>
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Spectator</title>. 341, 350, 356</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Stedman, E. C. 341, 343, 355</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Stephen, K. 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Stoddard, R. H. 329, 337</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Strozzi, Ercole. 356</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Swinburne, Admiral. 337</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Swinburne, A. C. <list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
								<item rendition="#hang"><hi rendition=" #u">Satirical views of</hi>. 337, 358</item>
								<item rendition="#hang"><hi rendition="#u">Sexuality</hi>. 325, 326, 337</item>
								<item rendition="#hang"><hi rendition=" #u">Works</hi>. <list rendition="#noBullets"
										type="bullet">
										<item rendition="#hang"><title level="a">Age and Song: To Barry Cornwall,</title> 333</item>
										<item rendition="#hang"><title>Bothwell</title>, 342</item>
										<item rendition="#hang"><title>Chastelard</title>, 325</item>
										<item rendition="#hang">fragments related to a family joke, 319-320</item>
										<item rendition="#hang"><title level="a">Laugh and Lie Down,</title> 346</item>
										<item rendition="#hang"><title level="a">Memorial Verses on the Death of William Bell Scott,</title>
											362</item>
										<item rendition="#hang"><title level="a">Temple of Janus,</title> 323</item>
										<item rendition="#hang"><title level="a">Unhappy Revenge,</title> 346</item>
										<item rendition="#hang"><title>A Year's Letters</title> (<title>Love's Cross
												Currents</title>), 337</item>
									</list></item>
							</list></item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Swinburne, I. 355</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Swinburne, Lady. 336, 363</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="t">
					<list rendition=" #noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Taylor, B. 329, 337</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Taylor, H. 353, 355, 356</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Tennyson, Lady. 362</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Thomas, F. D. 357</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Thomson, J. 333</item>
						<item rendition="#hang"><title>Times</title>. 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Trevelyan, Lady. 325, 326</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Tytler, S. 351</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="v">
					<list rendition="#noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Vacquarie, A. 349</item>
					</list>
				</div>
				<div xml:id="w">
					<list rendition=" #noBullets" type="bullet">
						<item rendition="#hang">Watts-Dunton, W. T. 340, 342, 343, 344, 345, 346, 348, 358, 360, 361,
							362, 364, 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Waugh, F. G. 340</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Wheeler, S. 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Whistler, J. M. 326</item>
					    <item xml:id="id02" rendition="#hang">White, W. H. 365</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Winter, H. E. 348</item>
						<item rendition="#hang">Wright, T. 367</item>
					</list>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="navigation">
				<p rendition="#center">
					<ref type="simple" target="#a">A</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#B">B</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#c">C</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#d">D</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#e">E</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#f">F</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#g">G</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#h">H</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#I">I</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#j">J</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#k">K</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#l">L</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#m">M</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#nn">N</ref> | O | <ref type="simple"
						target="#p">P</ref> | Q | <ref type="simple"
						target="#r">R</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#s">S</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#t">T</ref> | U | <ref type="simple"
						target="#v">V</ref> | <ref type="simple"
						target="#w">W</ref> | X | Y | Z
				</p>
			</div>
            </div>
                <div xml:id="appendixb">
                    <index indexName="nav"/>
                    <head rendition="#center #styled">Appendix B</head>
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>Letter 197. p. 330. Gentlemen’s <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            Gentleman’s</item>
                        <item>Letter 310A. p. 333. <title>The English Vice</title>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> expanded to <title>The English
                                Vice</title> (London: Duckworth, 1978).</item>
                        <item>Letter 475. p. 340. J. C. <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> John
                            Camden</item>
                        <item>Letter 1140. p. 354. <title>TOL</title>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <title>TOLOP</title></item>
                        <item>
                            <!-- jawalsh: removed extra period -->Letter 1605. p. 362. william <hi
                                rendition="#u">should be</hi> William</item>
                        <item>Letter 1767. p. 366. her <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> for
                            her</item>
                        <item>
                            <p>The following entries should be added:</p>
                            <list type="bullet">
                              <item>20. To Lady Jane Henrietta Swinburne [February 22] 1860 (<title>Letters</title>, I, 30)<lb/>
                                In 2008 Bonhams sold five letters from Sir John Franklin to Captain Swinburne, Swinburne’s father and, at the time, 1832, Franklin’s second in command.  The description of the lot (#156, Auction 16202; June 24, 2008; <ptr target="https://www.bonhams.com/auctions/16202/lot/156/"/>) notes that Captain Swinburne’s connection to Sir John Franklin might have had a bearing on Swinburne’s composition in 1860 of “The Death of Sir John Franklin“; it also suggests that Swinburne’s nickname, Hadji, might have reflected his father’s bemused recollection of his and Franklin’s negotiations with Hadji Pietro, the head of an irregular army seeking to be cut in on duties on currants as the newly independent Greece sought them as well. Both suggestions seem plausible.
                              </item>
                              <item>492. To Theodore Watts December 1, 1873	(<title>Letters</title>, II, 260)
                                <p>
                                Francis J. Sypher has elaborated Cecil Lang’s note regarding a lost article on Swinburne by the American journalist Olive Harper (Helen Burrell D’Apery [1843-1915]) in 1873.</p>
                                <p>
                                Sypher very kindly sent me a copy of his privately printed <title>Swinburne &amp; Olive Harper: The American ‘Interview’ from 1873</title> (New York: 2012) where he explores the circumstances surrounding Harper’s account of meeting Swinburne as published in a number of newspapers in America and even in Australia.  Sypher’s booklet reprints the version that he tracked down in the <title>Cincinnati Commercial</title> (July 21, 1873, p. 2), “London Literary Nobs.”   Although Sypher explores the several reasons to question whether the encounter occurred, he and I both tend to believe it did.  As Sypher says, “it is not impossible that [Harper] could have met” Swinburne between the middle of May and June 5, 1873:
                                  <cit  rendition="#blockquote">
                                <quote>
                                  <p>
                                Swinburne I have met also.  Somehow, he does not strike me pleasantly.  He is, I think, fearfully ugly, and has nervousness about him that makes you wish he would keep still just one moment.  Swinburne lives with his father, a short distance out of town.  Every now and then he escapes from rigid parental authority, takes a run up to London, and has what he calls a time.  We in California would call it a ‘spree.’  But he seems to have the kindest feelings for his fellow men.
                                  </p>
                                  <p>
                                To see this famous poet (Swinburne) [<foreign rendition="#i">sic</foreign>] write is a terrible experience.  He took a sudden inspiration in my room one day, and, without a word of explanation or apology, seated himself at my writing table, displaced all my things, and commenced writing.  His whole face worked vehemently; he pounded steadily with his left hand on the table, and his feet kept time in unison with his body to the monotonous thumping.  As soon as he had finished, he jumped up, seized his hat, and with a hurried ‘good-bye,’ rushed off to find his friend Watts, to whom
                                  </p>
                                </quote>
                                </cit>
                                </p>
                              </item>
                                <item>1313. To Andrew Chatto February 15, 1885 (<title>Letters</title>, V, 99)<lb/>
                                    The copy of <title>Passages in the Early Military Life of General George T. Napier</title>, ed. W. C. E. Napier (London: John Murray, 1884), which Swinburne requested of Andrew Chatto was for a birthday gift for Bertie Mason, whose eleventh birthday was February 4, 1885. The volume is now in my collection and is inscribed “Herbert Walter Mason / from his affectionate friend / Algernon Charles Swinburne / February, 1885.”</item>
                                <item>1418.  To the Editor of <title>The Times</title> May 3 [1887] (<title>Letters</title>, V, 188-190)<lb/>
                                    This letter was reprinted in <title>The Birmingham Daily Post</title>, 7 May 1887.</item>
                                
                                <item>1646. To Edmund Gosse June 29 [1894]
                                    (<title>Letters</title>, VI, 69)
                                    <lb/>This letter had been printed in part in
                                    <title>The New York Times</title>, 17 July 1894, p. 5.
                                </item>
                                <item>1784.  To Mario Borsa   March 18, 1902 [<hi rendition="#i">sic</hi> for 1903] (<title>Letters</title>, VI, 166)<lb/>
                                    Most of this letter was printed in Borsa’s <title>The English Stage of Today</title>, trans. Selwyn Brinton (London: John Lane, 1908), p. 202. 
                                </item>
                            </list>
                        </item>
                        <!-- Delete at the request of Terry Meyers: -->
                        <!--
                        <item>1870. To the clerical comments about Swinburne
                                at his death (<title>Letters</title>, VI, 229-231) should be added a
                                note:
                                <p> The controversy over an Anglican burial for Swinburne and the
                                    denunciation of him by the Vice-Dean of Canterbury Cathedral for
                                    the pollution he brought to English poetry (<title>Letters</title>, VI, 231)
                                    was echoed in 1924, when Thomas Hardy mocked the Dean of
                                    Westminster Abbey for refusing to allow a plaque to Byron in
                                    Poets’ Corner. In “A Refusal,” Hardy has the Dean comment that
                                    next thing you know he’ll be asked to consider others:
                                    <quote rendition="#blockquote #nq"><lg><l> ’Twill next be expected</l><l> That I get erected</l><l> To Shelley a tablet</l><l> In some niche or gablet.</l><l> Then—what makes my skin burn,</l><l> Yea, forehead to chin burn—</l><l> That I ensconce Swinburne.</l></lg></quote></p>
                           
                        </item>
                        -->
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="li1">
                    <index indexName="nav"/>
                    <head rendition="#center #styled">Vol I.—The Less Important</head>
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>To the “Short Titles of Works Cited” (pp. xi-xiii) <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> added:<lb/>
                            <bibl>
                                <author>Helen Rossetti Angeli</author>, <title>Pre-Raphaelite
                                    Twilight: The Story of Charles Augustus Howell</title> (St.
                                Clair Shores, MI: Scholarly Press, 1971) <hi rendition="#b"
                                    >Pre-Raphaelite Twilight</hi>
                            </bibl>
                        </item>
                        <item>p. xii. l. 23. Rooksby <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#b">Rooksby</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>P. xv, note 2. The title of the anthology edited by Jerome McGann and
                            Charles L. Sligh is <title>Algernon Charles Swinburne: Major Poems and
                                Selected Prose</title>. </item>
                        <item>p. xv. In l. 3, wife Edith <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> wife,
                            Edith,</item>
                        <item>p. xxiv. l. 1. Cirlce <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> Circle</item>
                        <item>Letter 13A. p. 6. In the date, September 10 <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> 10 September </item>
                        <item>Letter 16C. p. 10. In the address, Capheaton should moved to just
                            above the date</item>
                        <item>Letter 90C. p. 50. In note2, , see <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            (see</item>
                        <item>Letter 129A. p. 68. Delete note 1 as redundant</item>
                        <item>Letter 134B. p. 71. In the head note, charles <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> Charles</item>
                        <item>Letter 143A. p. 75. In note 3, delete Algernon Charles
                            Swinburne</item>
                        <item>Letter 186C. p. 98. In note 2, delete Algernon Charles
                            Swinburne</item>
                        <item>Letter 221A. p. 110. In note 2, delete (Algernon Charles Swinburne,
                                <title>Bothwell: A Tragedy</title> (London: Chatto and Windus,
                            1874))</item>
                        <item>Letter 244A. p. 117. The figures should be aligned more
                            squarely</item>
                        <item>Letter 309A. p. 165. In line 7, [”]Our <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> [“]Our </item>
                        <item>Letter 337C. p. 178. In the text note, the <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> The</item>
                        <item>Letter 356C. p. 190. In note 1, Henley <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#i">Henley</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 371B. p. 206. In note 1, [21 September 1870] <hi
                                rendition="#u">should be</hi> 21 September [1870] </item>
                        <item>Letter 388A. p. 214. In l. 2, Twilight[“] <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> Twilight[”]</item>
                        <item>Letter 394B. p. 218. In note 1, <hi rendition="#i">Reminiscences</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#i">Reminiscences</hi>,</item>
                        <item>Letter 396A. p. 218. In the head note, [?] <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> (?) </item>
                        <item>
                            <!-- jawalsh: check --> Letter 430C. p. 242. The”Wshing” figures,
                            shillings and pence, should be so aligned</item>
                        <item>
                            <!-- jawalsh: changed 2/3's to two-thirds --> Letter 453A. p. 262.
                            There’s a mistaken blank at the end of a line about two thirds of the
                            way down the page</item>
                        <item>Letter 455A p. 267. In note 14, delete <title>The Letters of John
                                Addington Symonds</title>
                        </item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="li2">
                    <index indexName="nav"/>
                    <head rendition="#center #styled">Vol. II.—The Less Important</head>
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>Letter 627A. p. 21. In note 7, <title>Essays and Studies</title>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <title>ES</title> (1875)</item>
                        <item>Letter 642B. p. 20. Note 1 should be deleted as redundant</item>
                        <item>Letter 668A. p. 39. In note 2, delete <title>Swinburne: Portrait of a
                                Poet</title>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 687A. p. 53. The letter from Swinburne that Powell mentions is
                            untraced.</item>
                        <item>Letter 728. p. 73. In note 5, delete the extraneous ()’s</item>
                        <item>Letter 741A. p. 77. In note 5, expand “Hake and Compton-Rickett” to
                            Thomas Hake and Arthur Compton Rickett, ed., <title>The Letters of
                                Algernon Charles Swinburne with Some Personal Recollections</title>
                            (London: John Murray, 1918).</item>
                        <item>Letter 760A p. 88. In note 2, <title>Essays and Studies</title>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <title>ES</title> (1875)</item>
                        <item>Letter 836A. p. 117. Mourning Stationery <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> mourning stationery</item>
                        <item>Letter 847A. p. 123. In note 1, expand “Gooch and Thatcher” to Bryan
                            N. S. Gooch and David S. Thatcher, <title>Musical Settings of Late
                                Victorian and Modern British Literature: A Catalogue</title> (New
                            York: Garland Pub., 1976).</item>
                        <item>Letter 848A p. 124. In note 3, Maccoll <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> MacColl</item>
                        <!--    <item>Letter 874A p. 132. In note 3, 1877 <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> 1877,</item> -->
                        <item>Letter 874A. p. 132. In note 3, 8 August, 1877 <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> 8 August 1877, </item>
                        <item>Letter 880B. p. 134. In the head note, delete Mrs.</item>
                        <item>Letter 889A. p. 140. In note 1, expand “<title>Monckton
                                Milnes</title>” to <title>Monckton Milnes: The Flight of
                                Youth</title> (London: Constable, 1949)</item>
                        <item>Letter 913A. p. 149. In the head note, Swinburne <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> , Swinburne</item>
                        <item>Letter 944A. p. 168. In note 1, ‘ <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            ’</item>
                        <item>Letter 978F. p. 182. In note 3, artefacts <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> artifacts</item>
                        <item>Letter 978F. p. 183. In note 6, 1873 <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> 1873,</item>
                        <item>Letter 989C. p. 193. In note 8, Library <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> Museum</item>
                        <item>Letter 996A. p. 202. In the return address, ,S <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> , S</item>
                        <item>Letter 1001B. p. 206. In note 2, Letters <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> see Letters</item>
                        <item>Letter 1011E. p. 222. In note 3, or <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            or,</item>
                        <item>Letter 1032A. p. 234. In the text note, Library <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> University</item>
                        <item>Letter 1034A. p. 235. In the return address, Hill, <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> Hill.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1059A. p. 252. In note 1, Libraries <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> Libraries,</item>
                        <item>Letter 1077A. p. 264. The salutation is in the wrong font</item>
                        <item>Letter 1081B. p. 268. In the PS, <hi rendition="#i">return</hi> . <hi
                                rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#i">return</hi>.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1110C. p. 276. In the text note, Fran-klin <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> Frank-lin</item>
                        <item>Letter 1205A. p. 321. In the text note, University <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> University.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1273A. p. 363. Expand “<title>Life and Letters of Theodore
                                Watts-Dunton</title>” to Thomas Hake and Arthur Compton-Rickett,
                                <title>Life and Letters of Theodore Watts-Dunton</title>, 2 vols.
                            (London: T. C. &amp; E. C. Jack, 1916).</item>
                        <item>Letter 1273A. p. 364. In note 1, the title should be expanded to
                                    <bibl><title>Life and Letters of Benjamin Jowett</title>, eds.
                                    <editor role="editor">Evelyn Abbott</editor> and <editor
                                    role="editor">Lewis Campbell</editor>, <extent>2 vols</extent>.
                                    (<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>: <publisher>J. Murray</publisher>,
                                    <date>1897</date>).</bibl></item>
                        <item>Letter 1295A. p. 372. In the head note, the <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> The</item>
                        <item>Letter 1312A. p. 375. In note 2, delete John Y.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1322B. p. 380. In note 1, enclose the citation to <title>The
                                Times</title> in ()’s</item>
                        <item>Letter 1322C. p. 382. In note 3, <title>CRC</title>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <title>CR </title>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1393B p. 417. In note 2, p. 6 as <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> p. 6, as</item>
                        <item>Letter 1407C. p. 423. In the return address, The Pines should be
                            centered above the date.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1407D. p. 424. In the head note, [?] <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> (?)</item>
                        <item>Letter 1409A. p. 426. In note 1, 501). <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> 501)).</item>
                        <item>Letter 1526A. p. 485. In note 2, delete John Y.</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                <div xml:id="li3">
                    <index indexName="nav"/>
                    <head rendition="#center #styled">Vol. III.—The Less Important</head>
                    <list type="bullet">
                        <item>Letter 1540B. p. 12. In note 1, below; <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> below,</item>
                        <item>Letter 1558A. p. 25. In the note, Spielman <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> Spielmann</item>
                        <item>Letter 1563B. p. 6. In note 3, delete A. C. Swinburne</item>
                        
                        <item>Letter 1601A. p. 41. In note 4, ,and <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> , and</item>
                        <item>Letter 1619B. p. 49. In text note, University <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> University.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1654C. p. 84. In note 22, 1894 <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> 1894, above,</item>
                        <item>Letter 1654C. p. 84. In note 22, 1895 <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> 1895, below,</item>
                        <!-- <item>Letter 1656C. p. 88. In note 1, delete George Eric Mackay</item>-->
                        <item>Letter 1656C. p. 88. In note 1, delete George Eric Mackay</item>
                        <item>Letter 1672A. p. 98. In note 1, delete the second sentence</item>
                        <item>Letter 1679A. p. 99. In note 1, 1904) <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> 1904))</item>
                        <item>Letter 1695B. p. 110. In note 1, 7.45 <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> 7:45</item>
                        <item>Letter 1713A. p. 115. The date should be to the far left of the
                            page</item>
                        <item>Letter 1747A. p. 165. In note 1, delete the extra ) at the end</item>
                        <item>Letter 1767A. p. 186. In the return address, Westcliffe-on-Sea, should
                            be centered.</item>
                        <item>Letter 1773D. p. 202. In note 5, Bookmen <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> Bookman</item>
                        <item>Letter 1774E. p. 213. Delete note 1 as redundant</item>
                        <item>Letter 1774H. p. 217. The heading is in the wrong font and should be
                            italicized and centered</item>
                        <item>Letter 1779D. p. 223. In note 5, <title>Autobiogaphical Notes</title>
                            should be expanded to William Bell Scott, <title>Autobiographical Notes
                                of the Life of William Bell Scott</title>, ed. William Minto, 2
                            vols. (London: Osgood, McIlvaine 1892)</item>
                        <item>Letter 1807A. p. 241. In the head note, Swinburne <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> Swinburne,</item>
                        <item>Letter 1809A. p. 248. In note 1, 257,A <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> 257, A</item>
                        <item>Letter 1826A p. 268. In the text note, the <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> The</item>
                        <item>Letter 1826C. p. 271. In note 2, <title>PB</title> I <hi
                                rendition="#u">should be</hi>
                            <title>PB</title>(1866)</item>
                        <item>Letter 1827E. p. 276. In the head note, delete , from
                            Swinburne</item>
                        <item>Letter 476B. p. 282. In the penultimate line, publicat <hi
                                rendition="#super">n</hi>
                            <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> publicat<hi rendition="#super">n</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Letter 1842A. p. 284. In note 1, ‘Christabel’ <hi rendition="#u"
                                >should be</hi> ‘Christabel’,</item>
                        <item>Letter 1842A. p. 285. In note 2, Leeds <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> Leeds University</item>
                        <item>Letter 1845C. p. 287. In the head note, delete , from
                            Swinburne</item>
                        <item>Letter 1899. p. 314. In note 1, realted <hi rendition="#u">should
                                be</hi> related</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
                
                <div xml:id="general_issues">
                    <index indexName="nav"/>
                    <head rendition="#center #styled">General Issues</head>
                    <list>
                    <item>In a number of text notes, there is a space before a semi-colon. See,
                        for example, Letters 414B</item>
                    <item>In a number of notes, a space is missing between p. or pp. and the
                        numbers. See, for example, Letter 157A, note 3</item>
                    <item>In a number of head notes, A. C. has come out wrongly as A .C. See
                        Letters l39A, 283A, 343A, 474A, 1011D, 1118A</item>
                    <item>
                      <!-- jawalsh: no underlining? --> In a number of head notes, Copy <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> copy: see Letters 830D, 1618A, 1639A, 1769A, 1894</item>
                    <item>In several head notes, []’s <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> ()’s: see Letters 396A,
                        1407D</item>
                    <item>In several text notes, “Printed” <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> “printed”; see Letters
                        281A, 1055D</item>
                    <item>In a number of letters, “The Pines.” <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> “The Pines,”: see
                        Letters 1034A, 1052D, 1203D, 1216A, 1245B, 1497A</item>
                    <item>In a number of letters, “The Pines,” <hi rendition="#u">should be</hi> better centered: see
                        Letters 1259A, 1260B, 1332A, 1407D</item>
                    <item>In several notes, <title>Selection</title> or
                        <title>Selections</title> should be <title>A Selection</title>; see Letters 103A,
                        430B</item>
                    <item>In several notes, <title>Catalogue</title> should be <title>A
                    Catalogue</title>; see Letters 978F, 1685C, 1612B</item>
                    </list>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
