<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="swinburne.rnc" type="compact"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../../tei2html/p5/css/tei.css"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI [
<!ENTITY title "Project Information">
<!ENTITY id "acs0000508-01">
]>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="&id;">

    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>&title;</title>
                <author>
                	<persName xml:id="jawalsh" key="jawalsh">John A. Walsh</persName>
                </author>
                <editor role="editor">
                    <persName key="jawalsh">John A. Walsh</persName>
                </editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Encoded by</resp>
                    <name>John A. Walsh</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                href="includes/publicationStmt.xml"/>
            <seriesStmt>
                <title>The Swinburne Project: An Electronic Edition of the Works of Algernon Charles
                    Swinburne</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Edited by</resp>
                    <name>John A. Walsh</name>
                </respStmt>
            </seriesStmt>
        	<sourceDesc>
        		<biblStruct>
        			<analytic>
        				<author><persName key="jawalsh">John A. Walsh</persName></author>
        				<title>&title;</title>
        			</analytic>
        			
        			<monogr>
        				<title>The Algernon Charles Swinburne Project</title>
        				
        				<editor><persName key="jawalsh">John A. Walsh</persName></editor>
        				<imprint>
        					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        						href="includes/publisher.xml"/>
        					<xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
        						href="includes/pubPlace.xml"/>
        					<date xml:id="sort_date" when="2012"/>
        				</imprint>
        			</monogr>
        		</biblStruct>
        	</sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <xi:include xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="includes/tagsDecl.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="includes/collex_genres.xml" xpointer="element(collex_genres)"/>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <textClass>
                <catRef target="#collex_genre_review"/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:id="&id;-content">
        <pb n="1" rendition="#suppress" facs="dummy"/>
         <body xml:id="home_content" rend="margin-left:0;margin-right:0;">
      <div xml:id="overview">
          <index indexName="nav"/>
						<head>Overview</head>
						
						<p><title>The Swinburne Project</title> aims to create and provide access to
							high-quality texts of the wide range of literary and critical works by
							Swinburne, an important and influential Victorian cultural figure. These
							texts constitute the <title>Project</title>'s textual/documentary core,
							around which is built a digital, paratextual framework of investigation
							and performance. These paratextual performances include information
							visualizations, maps (geographic and topical), timelines, textual
							analysis interfaces and algorithms, and more.</p>
					</div>
         			<div xml:id="peer_review">
         				<index indexName="nav"/>
         				<head>Peer Review</head>
         				<p><title>The Swinburne Project</title> has been peer reviewed by NINES. The NINES Web site describes the goals of the organization:</p>
         				<p>
         					<cit rendition="#blockquote">
         						<quote>
         							<p rend="margin-bottom:0;">NINES (<hi rendition="#b">N</hi>etworked <hi rendition="#b">I</hi>nfrastructure of <hi rendition="#b">N</hi>ineteenth-Century <hi rendition="#b">E</hi>lectronic <hi rendition="#b">S</hi>cholarship) is a scholarly organization devoted to forging links between the material archive of the nineteenth century and the digital research environment of the twenty-first. Our activities are driven by three primary goals:
         								<list rend="margin-bottom:0;">
         									<item>to serve as a <ref target="http://www.nines.org/about/scholarship/peer-review/">peer-reviewing body</ref> for digital work in the long 19th-century (1770-1920), British and American;</item>
         								<item>to support scholars’ priorities and best practices in the creation of digital research materials;</item>
         								<item>to develop software tools for new and traditional forms of research and critical analysis.</item>
         								</list>
         							</p>
         						</quote>
         						<bibl rend="margin-left:20em;">(<title level="a"><ref target="http://www.nines.org/about/what-is-nines/">What is NINES?</ref></title>)</bibl>
         					</cit>
         				</p>
         				<p>NINES provides a detailed explanation of their <ref target="http://www.nines.org/about/scholarship/peer-review/">peer review</ref> processes and standards, that begins with an explanation of the motivation for providing this peer review framework to the digital humanities community:
         				<cit rendition="#blockquote">
         					<quote><p>Digital humanities projects have long lacked a framework for peer review and thus have often had difficulty establishing their credibility as true scholarship. NINES exists in part to address this situation by instituting a robust system of review by some of the most <ref target="http://www.nines.org/about/scholarship/editorial-boards/">respected scholars</ref> in the field of nineteenth-century studies, British and American.</p>
         						<p rend="margin-bottom:0;">NINES provides peer-review of digital resources and archives created by scholars in nineteenth-century studies. Our <ref target="http://www.nines.org/about/scholarship/editorial-boards/">Editorial Boards</ref> locate reviewers to evaluate both the intellectual content and the technical structure of each project submitted for inclusion in NINES.</p>
         					</quote><bibl rend="margin-left:20em;">(<title level="a"><ref target="http://www.nines.org/about/scholarship/peer-review/">Peer Review</ref></title>)</bibl>
         				</cit>
         				</p>
         				<p>For more information about the NINES review process see their full <title level="a"><ref target="http://www.nines.org/about/scholarship/peer-review/">Peer Review</ref></title> document.</p>
         			</div>
					<div xml:id="people">
					    <index indexName="nav"/>
						<head>People</head>
						<p><ref target="http://www.slis.indiana.edu/faculty/jawalsh">John A. Walsh</ref>,
							Editor and Project Director, is an Assistant Professor of Library and
							Information Science and an Adjunct Assistant Professor of English at
							Indiana University. As part of the enterprise known as “digital
							humanities” Walsh designs and builds things, things like <title>The
								Swinburne Project</title> and its ancillary efforts. He has published
							articles on digital humanities topics, Unicode and the language of
							alchemy, Swinburne, holy icons of Eastern Christianity, and comic
							books.</p>
						<p>Over the years, many graduate students and assistants have contributed to
							the project, assisting with encoding, proof-reading, documentation, and other tasks: 
						<list rend="margin-top:1em;">
							<item>Audre Azuolas</item>
							<item>Jason Evan Groth</item>
							<item>Ryan Lee</item>
							<item>Elizabeth Munson</item>
							<item>Brian Norberg</item>
							<item>Adam Ploshay</item>
							<item>Alan Rhoda</item>
							<item>Xingxing Yao</item>
							<item>Alice Wei</item>
						</list></p>
						<p>The Swinburne Project is supported by Indiana University's Libraries and
							Digital Library Program. Many individuals from the Digital Library
							Program have contributed their advice and expertise to the project: 
						<list rend="margin-top:1em;">
							<item>Michelle Dalmau, Digital Projects and Usability Librarian, Digital
								Library Program</item>
							<item>Kara Alexander, Digital Media Specialist, Digital Library
								Program</item>
							<item>Will Cowan, Associate Director for Digital Software Development,
								Digital Library Program</item>
							<item>Mike Durbin, Programmer/Analyst, Digital Library Infrastructure,
								Digital Library Program</item>
							<item>Jon Dunn, Director of Library Technologies and Digital Libraries,
								Digital Library Program</item>
							<item>David Jiao, Programmer/Analyst, Digital Library Program</item>
							<item>Jenn Riley, Metadata Librarian, Digital Library Program
								(2000-2010)</item>
							<item>Brian Wheeler, System Administrator, Digital Library Program</item>
						</list>
						</p>
					</div>
         	<div xml:id="note_on_the_texts">
         		<index indexName="nav"/>
         		<head>A Note on the Texts</head>
         		<p>           
         			The core of <title>The Swinburne Project</title> consists of digital representations of Swinburne's works. Around this core are assembled multiple paratextual layers that explore various documentary and literary dimensions of the texts. The digital representations of Swinburne's works have been prepared according to the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative</ref> (<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/">TEI</ref>) <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index-toc.html"><title>Guidelines for Electronic Text Encoding and Interchange</title></ref>.
         		</p>         
         		<p>           
         			While we attempt a diplomatic faithfulness to the source texts, we are conscious that we are necessarily creating new texts with an ever-growing amount of scholarly commentary, annotation, intervention, and additional paratextual layers. </p>
         		<p>There is no reliable scholarly edition of Swinburne complete works or complete poems. The present edition of <title>The Swinburne Project</title> aims to fill that void. Edmund Gosse and the bibliographer and forger Thomas J. Wise edited the <soCalled>Bonchurch Edition</soCalled> of <title>The Complete Works of Algernon Charles Swinburne</title> (London: Heinemann, 1924-27) in twenty volumes, but their edition is considered unreliable, <cit><quote>misleading in arrangement and omissions and … often corrupt</quote> <bibl>(<ref target="#hyder1970">Hyder</ref> xi)</bibl></cit>. Wise's <title>Bibliography</title>, published separately and as volume twenty of the “Bonchurch Edition,” is an important and useful source of information on Swinburne's published works, though marred by the inclusion of spurious pamphlets forged by Wise himself. In the absence of subsequent authoritative editions, one turns to documents that Swinburne himself saw through the press.
         		</p>
         		
         		<div xml:id="note_on_the_text_poems">
         			<index indexName="nav"/>
         			<head>Published Poems</head>
         			<p>
         				The text of Swinburne's published poems are based on the six-volume <title>Poems of Algernon Charles Swinburne</title> (London: Chatto &amp; Windus, 1904), which gathers all the individual collections of poetry from <title>Poems and Ballads, First Series</title> (1866) through <title>A Channel Passage and Other Poems</title> (1904). Also included in the six-volume <title>Poems</title> are the lyrical dramas <title>Atalanta in Calydon</title> (1865) and <title>Erechtheus</title> (1876) and the long Arthurian narratives <title>Tristram of Lyonesse</title> (1882) and <title>The Tale of Balen</title> (1896).</p>
         			<p>Swinburne himself saw this collected edition through the press. The 1904 <title>Poems</title> is a reliable text and is the standard text that has typically been cited in Swinburne scholarship (although we hope that future scholarship will cite texts from <title>The Swinburne Project</title>). <title>The Swinburne Project</title> edition corrects errors in the source texts as they are identified. These errors and corrections are recorded in the TEI/XML encoding. For instance, the 1904 text of <title level="a"><ref target="x-spid:acs0000001-01-i003">A Ballad of Death</ref></title> reads <q>Her curled air had the wave of sea-water</q> for <q>Her curled hair had the wave of sea-water.</q>  See the encoding that records this error and the supplied correction: 
         				<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<l n="36">
	Her curled 
	<choice>
		<sic>air</sic>
		<corr>hair</corr>
	</choice> 
	had the wave of sea-water
</l>
         				</egXML>
         			</p>
         		</div>
         		<div xml:id="note_on_the_text_lcc">
         			<index indexName="nav"/>
         			<head><title>Love's Cross-Currents</title></head>
         			<p>Swinburne's single published novel, <title>Love's Cross Currents</title>, was originally serialized as <title>A Year's Letters</title>, under the pseudonym <soCalled>Mrs. Horace Manners</soCalled>, in <title>The Tatler</title> from August 25th to December 29th, 1877. The text here is based on the 1905 edition, which appeared as <title>Love's Cross-Currents: A Year's Letters</title>, under Swinburne's name, published by Chatto &amp; Windus.</p>
         		</div>
         	</div>
					<div xml:id="standards">
					    <index indexName="nav"/>
						<head>Standards and Methodologies</head>
						<div xml:id="encoded_text">
						    <index indexName="nav"/>
							<head>The Encoded Text</head>
							<div xml:id="tei_xml">
							    <index indexName="nav"/>
								<head>TEI/XML</head>
								<p>The technological, methodological, and performative foundation of
									the
										<title>The Swinburne Project</title> is the encoded text. The
									standard technology for authoring encoded texts is the
									eXtensible Markup Language, or XML, which was introduced in 1998.
									XML is built upon an existing standard for encoded texts, the Standard
									Generalized Markup Language, or SGML, which was adopted as a
									standard by the International Standards Organization in 1986.
									SGML itself was built upon a prior technology, IBM's Generalized
									Markup Language (GML), developed in the 1960s by Charles
									Goldfarb, Edward Mosher, and Raymond Lorie. </p>
								<p>XML is a syntax for encoded texts. The syntax supports an
									unlimited number of targeted XML schemas or vocabularies. The XML
									vocabulary used by <title>The Swinburne Project</title> is the
											<title><ref
											target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/"
											>Text Encoding Initiative P5: Guidelines for Electronic
											Text Encoding and Interchange</ref></title>. The <title>TEI
										Guidelines</title> are a mature conceptual model for digital
									representation of a vast array of documents: inscriptions and
									papyri; illuminated manuscripts; authorial holograph
									manuscripts; correspondence; printed books of prose, verse, and
									drama; critical editions; born-digital documents; and more. The
										<title>TEI Guidelines</title>:
								<cit rendition="#blockquote">
									<quote>make recommendations about suitable ways of representing
										those features of textual resources which need to be
										identified explicitly in order to facilitate processing by
										computer programs. In particular, they specify a set of
										markers (or tags) which may be inserted in the electronic
										representation of the text, in order to mark the text
										structure and other features of interest.</quote>
								</cit>
								</p>
								<!-- <ptr type="biblref" target="#tei2010"></ptr>-->
								<p> The <title>TEI Guidelines</title> are widely used in the digital
									humanities and academic library communities and are maintained
									by the <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/">TEI Consortium</ref>, an
									international body whose membership includes universities;
									libraries and other cultural heritage institutions; scholarly
									projects; and individual scholars, librarians, and
									technologists. The <title>TEI Guidelines</title> are implemented
									as a set of modules, including modules for general categories of
									documents, such as prose, drama, verse, and dictionaries. The
										<title>Guidelines</title> also provide additional modules that
									address more specific textual features and metadata
									requirements, such as names and dates, manuscript description,
									linking, textual criticism, and so on. And in the most recent
									version, the <title>Guidelines</title> provide special XML
									elements and attributes for linking transcriptions to facsimile
									page images. From these many available modules, one selects a
									subset that meets the needs of a particular document, project,
									collection, or analytical approach.</p>
								<p><title>The Swinburne Project</title> uses the following TEI
									modules:
								<list rend="margin-top:1em;">
									<item>tei</item>
									<item>core (Elements common to all TEI documents)</item>
									<item>header (The TEI Header)</item>
									<item>textstructure (Default text structure)</item>
									<item>figures (Tables, formulæ, and figures)</item>
									<item>namesdates (Names and dates)</item>
									<item>linking (Linking, segmentation and alignment)</item>
									<item>transcr (Transcription of primary sources)</item>
									<item>msdescription (Manuscript Description)</item>
									<item>analysis (Simple analytic mechanisms)</item>
									<item>drama (Performance texts)</item>
									<item>verse (Verse structures)</item>
									<item>tagdocs (Documentation of TEI modules)</item>
									<item>dictionaries (Dictionaries)</item>
								</list>
								</p>
								<p>The TEI ODD file, which defines the TEI
									configuration/customization, and the resulting Relax NG schema
									are available for <ref target="/swinburne/downloads.jsp">download</ref>.</p>
							</div>
							<div xml:id="glossary">
							    <index indexName="nav"/>
								<head>Glossary</head>
								<p>Vocabulary that is likely to be unfamiliar to modern readers has
									been glossed in a separate Swinburne Glossary TEI/XML document
									that uses the TEI's dictionaries module. Glossary entries are
									linked from the primary source texts and appear as pop-up notes
									in the HTML versions of the texts. The presence of a glossary
									note is indicated by a degree symbol (°).</p>
							  <figure rendition="#center">
							    <head>Glossary entry pop-up note.</head>
									<graphic url="/swinburne/images/swinburne/swinburne_glossary.png"/>
										<figDesc>Example of glossary entry in browser interface.</figDesc>
							  </figure>
							</div>
							<div xml:id="topic_map">
							    <index indexName="nav"/>
							    <head>Topic Maps</head>
								<p>Topic Maps are another encoding standard, with an XML syntax, for
									encoding information about topics. The XML Topic Map (XTM) 1.0
									specification defines topics, and the related concept of
									subjects, as follows:
									<cit rendition="#blockquote">
								<quote>
									<p>A topic is a resource that acts as a proxy from some subject;
										it is the topic map system's representation of that
										subject.…</p>
									<p rend="margin-bottom:0;">A subject is anything that can be
										spoken about or conceived of by a human being. In the most
										generic sense, a subject is anything whatsoever, regardless
										of whether it exists or has any other specific
										characteristics, about which anything whatsoever may be
										asserted by any means whatsoever. In particular, it is
										anything about which the author of a topic map chooses to
										discourse.</p>
								</quote>
									<bibl rend="display:block; margin-top:0;text-indent:8em;">—<ptr target="http://www.topicmaps.org/xtm/"/></bibl>
									</cit>
								</p>
								<p>Topic Maps are used in <title>The Swinburne Project</title> to
									capture information about people, places, institutions, events,
									and works that are referenced in Swinburne's own writings. Topic
									Map entries are linked from the primary source texts and appear
									as pop-up notes in the HTML versions of the texts. The presence
									of a topical note is indicated by a degree symbol (°).</p>
							  <figure rendition="#center">
							    <head>Topic Map entry pop-up note. Information in
							      this example note includes birth and death dates, a short
							      description, and a link to Wikipedia article.</head>
									<graphic url="/swinburne/images/swinburne/swinburne_xtm.png"/>
										<figDesc>Example of topic map entry in browser interface.</figDesc>
							  </figure>
								</div>
							</div>
							<div xml:id="xslt" rend="margin-top:3em;">
							    <index indexName="nav"/>
							    <head>eXtensible Stylesheet Language Transformations (XSLT)</head>
								<p>XSLT is an XML-based language for transforming XML. XSLT is
									utilized throughout <title>The Swinburne Project</title> to
									perform the following transformations:
								<list rend="margin-top:1em;">
									<item>TEI/XML files representing physical volumes are decomposed
										and combined with metadata to create XML files representing
										individual works (e.g., poems or essays) within those
										physical volumes.</item>
									<item>TEI/XML files are transformed into METS (Metadata Encoding
										and Transmission Standard) files that support the
										page-turning and table-of-contents navigation features.</item>
									<item>TEI/XML files are transformed into HTML for display in web
										browsers. The TEI-to-HTML transformation also integrates
										information from the external glossary and topic map
										files.</item>
									<item>TEI/XML files are transformed into RDF metadata and plain
										text files for indexing by <ref target="http://www.nines.org/"
											>NINES</ref>, a federated, peer-reviewed collection of
										digital scholarship on the Nineteenth Century.</item>
								</list></p>
								<p>The <ref target="/swinburne/resources/tei2html.zip">TEI-to-HTML
										stylesheets</ref> are available for <ref
										target="/swinburne/downloads.jsp">download</ref>.</p>
							</div>
						</div>
						<div xml:id="webapp">
						    <index indexName="nav"/>
							<head>Web Application</head>
							<p><title>The Swinburne Project</title> web application is built upon the
									<ref target="http://xtf.cdlib.org/">eXtensible Text Framework</ref>
									(<ref target="http://xtf.cdlib.org/">XTF</ref>) from the California
								Digital Library. XTF is “a powerful open source platform for
								providing access to digital content” (<ref
									target="http://xtf.cdlib.org/">http://xtf.cdlib.org/</ref>). XTF is
								a Java web application and utilizes popular open source technologies
								such as the <ref target="http://lucene.apache.org/">Lucene</ref> search
								engine library and the <ref target="http://saxon.sourceforge.net/"
									>Saxon</ref> XSLT and XQuery processor. </p>
							<p><title>The Swinburne Project</title> deploys a heavily customized
								version of XTF. Many of the default XSLT stylesheets have been
								replaced with custom stylesheets. In particular, the TEI to HTML
								conversion is handled by the <ref
									target="/swinburne/resources/tei2html.zip">tei2html</ref> XSLT
								stylesheets discussed above, which were written specifically for
									<title>The Swinburne Project</title>. <title>The Swinburne
									Project</title> has also incorporated <ref
									target="http://metsnavigator.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/metsnavigator/"
									>METS Navigator</ref>, from Indiana University's <ref
									target="http://www.dlib.indiana.edu/">Digital Library Program</ref>,
								for navigating both the encoded texts and the facsimile page images. </p>
							<p> Sencha <ref target="http://www.sencha.com/products/extjs3/">Ext JS</ref>
								and Dyn-Web <ref target="http://www.dyn-web.com/code/tooltips/"
									>Tooltip</ref> JavaScript libraries are used. </p>
						</div>
         	<div xml:id="browsers">
         		<index indexName="nav"/>
         			<head>Supported Browsers</head>
         			<p><title>The Swinburne Project</title> uses current Web standards and technologies and requires a recent browser. Internet Explorer 8 or later, and recent versions of Safari, Firefox, and Chrome are all supported.</p>
         	</div>
         		<div xml:id="infrastructure">
						    <index indexName="nav"/>
							<head>Infrastructure</head>
							<p><title>The Swinburne Project</title> is hosted on Unix and Linux
								servers maintained and supported by the IU <ref
									target="http://www.dlib.indiana.edu">Digital Library Program</ref>
								(DLP) and the <ref target="http://www.slis.indiana.edu/">School of
									Library and Information Science</ref> (SLIS). </p>
							<div xml:id="backups">
							    <index indexName="nav"/>
								<head>Backups</head>
								<p>The digital documents (XML, HTML, CSS, code, etc.) are under SVN
									version control on DLP and SLIS servers.</p>
								<p>These documents and image files (primarily facsimile page images)
									are securely stored in Indiana University's <ref
									  target="https://pti.iu.edu/storage/sda">Scholarly Data
										Archive</ref>, a hierarchical storage management system with
									mirrored systems in Bloomington and Indianapolis.</p>
							</div>
					
					</div>
					<div xml:id="sandlot">
					    <index indexName="nav"/>
						<head><ref target="/swinburne/study.jsp">Tools &amp; Tactics</ref></head>
						<p>
							<ref target="/swinburne/study.jsp">Tools &amp; Tactics</ref> is a collection of digital research—visualizations, image and text analysis tools, and creative works—from <title>The Swinburne Project</title>. These research projects engage with and are informed by the edited and encoded text corpus of the <title>Swinburne Project</title>. 
					</p>
						<figure rendition="#center">
						  <head>Collage of items from <ref target="/swinburne/study.jsp">Tools &amp; Tactics</ref>.</head>
						
							<graphic url="/swinburne/images/swinburne/sandlot.png"/>
								<figDesc>Collage of items from Tools &amp; Tactics</figDesc>
						</figure>
						
					</div>
					<div xml:id="dedication" rend="text-align:center;">
					    <index indexName="nav"/>
						<head>Dedication</head>
						<p rend="font-style:italic;text-align:center;">For my beautiful Michelle,<lb />
						and our little ones—<lb />
							Patrick, Olivia, Mia,<lb />
							and baby Jude.</p>
					  <cit rendition="#block" rend="font-style:italic;margin-left:auto;margin-right:auto;text-align:left;width:14em;font-size:85%;font-family:'helvetica neue';">
					    <quote>
					      <lg>
					        <l>
					          <hi rendition="#sc">If </hi>love were what the rose is,</l>
					        <l rendition="#ti-1">And I were like the leaf,</l>
					        <l>Our lives would grow together</l>
					        <l>In sad or singing weather,</l>
					        <l>Blown fields or flowerful closes,</l>
					        <l rendition="#ti-1">Green pleasure or grey grief;</l>
					        <l>If love were what the rose is,</l>
					        <l rendition="#ti-1">And I were like the leaf.</l>
					      </lg>
					      <lg>
					        <l>If I were what the words are,</l>
					        <l rendition="#ti-1">And love were like the tune,</l>
					        <l>With double sound and single</l>
					        <l>Delight our lips would mingle,</l>
					        <l>With kisses glad as birds are</l>
					        <l rendition="#ti-1">That get sweet rain at noon;</l>
					        <l>If I were what the words are,</l>
					        <l rendition="#ti-1">And love were like the tune.</l>
					      </lg>
					    </quote>
					  </cit>

					</div>



    </body>
    	<back>
    		<div xml:id="works_cited">
    			<index indexName="nav"/>
    		<head rendition="#styled #center">Works Cited</head>
    			<listBibl>
    				<bibl xml:id="hyder1970">Hyder, Clyde K. <title level="a">Preface.</title> <title>Algernon Swinburne: The Critical Heritage</title>. Ed. Clyde K. Hyder. London: Routledge, 1970.</bibl>
    			</listBibl>
    		</div>
    	</back>
    </text>
</TEI>
